      The/O Project/O Gutenberg/O EBook/O of/O Anna/PERSON Karenina/PERSON,/O by/O Leo/PERSON Tolstoy/PERSON


no/O restrictions/O whatsoever/O./O You/O may/O copy/O it/O,/O give/O it/O away/O or/O re-use/O it/O
eBook/O or/O online/O at/O http://www.gutenberg.org/license/O./O



Title/O:/O Anna/PERSON Karenina/PERSON
Author/O:/O Leo/PERSON Tolstoy/PERSON
Release/O Date/O:/O July/O 01/O,/O 1998/O -LSB-/OEBook/O #/O1399/O-RSB-/O
Reposted/O:/O April/O 02/O,/O 2005/O -LSB-/Ocorrections/O,/O reposted/O to/O new/O folder/O structure/O
by/O David/PERSON Widger/PERSON-RSB-/O
Reposted/O:/O December/O 09/O,/O 2011/O -LSB-/Ocorrections/O-RSB-/O
Reposted/O:/O December/O 15/O,/O 2012/O -LSB-/Ocorrections/O,/O conversion/O to/O HTML/O-RSB-/O
Reposted/O:/O February/O 14/O,/O 2013/O -LSB-/Oconversion/O to/O XHTML/O Strict/O by/O David/PERSON Widger/PERSON-RSB-/O
Reposted/O:/O February/O 22/O,/O 2013/O -LSB-/Ocorrections/O,/O conversion/O to/O RST/O by/O Andrew/PERSON
Sly/PERSON-RSB-/O
Language/O:/O English/O
Character/O set/O encoding/O:/O UTF-8/O


***/O START/O OF/O THIS/O PROJECT/O GUTENBERG/O EBOOK/O ANNA/O KARENINA/O ***/O




Produced/O by/O David/PERSON Brannan/PERSON./O





                             Anna/PERSON Karenina/PERSON

                             by/O Leo/PERSON Tolstoy/PERSON




                    Translated/O by/O Constance/PERSON Garnett/PERSON




PART/O ONE/O



Chapter/O 1/O


Happy/O families/O are/O all/O alike/O;/O every/O unhappy/O family/O is/O unhappy/O in/O its/O own/O
way/O./O

Everything/O was/O in/O confusion/O in/O the/O Oblonskys/O'/O house/O./O The/O wife/O had/O
discovered/O that/O the/O husband/O was/O carrying/O on/O an/O intrigue/O with/O a/O French/O
girl/O,/O who/O had/O been/O a/O governess/O in/O their/O family/O,/O and/O she/O had/O announced/O to/O
her/O husband/O that/O she/O could/O not/O go/O on/O living/O in/O the/O same/O house/O with/O him/O./O
This/O position/O of/O affairs/O had/O now/O lasted/O three/O days/O,/O and/O not/O only/O the/O
husband/O and/O wife/O themselves/O,/O but/O all/O the/O members/O of/O their/O family/O and/O
household/O,/O were/O painfully/O conscious/O of/O it/O./O Every/O person/O in/O the/O house/O
felt/O that/O there/O was/O no/O sense/O in/O their/O living/O together/O,/O and/O that/O the/O
stray/O people/O brought/O together/O by/O chance/O in/O any/O inn/O had/O more/O in/O common/O
with/O one/O another/O than/O they/O,/O the/O members/O of/O the/O family/O and/O household/O of/O
the/O Oblonskys/O./O The/O wife/O did/O not/O leave/O her/O own/O room/O,/O the/O husband/O had/O not/O
been/O at/O home/O for/O three/O days/O./O The/O children/O ran/O wild/O all/O over/O the/O house/O;/O
the/O English/O governess/O quarreled/O with/O the/O housekeeper/O,/O and/O wrote/O to/O a/O
friend/O asking/O her/O to/O look/O out/O for/O a/O new/O situation/O for/O her/O;/O the/O man-cook/O
had/O walked/O off/O the/O day/O before/O just/O at/O dinner/O time/O;/O the/O kitchen-maid/O,/O and/O
the/O coachman/O had/O given/O warning/O./O

Three/O days/O after/O the/O quarrel/O,/O Prince/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON Oblonsky/PERSON--/OStiva/PERSON,/O
as/O he/O was/O called/O in/O the/O fashionable/O world/O--/Owoke/O up/O at/O his/O usual/O hour/O,/O
that/O is/O,/O at/O eight/O o'clock/O in/O the/O morning/O,/O not/O in/O his/O wife/O's/O bedroom/O,/O but/O
on/O the/O leather-covered/O sofa/O in/O his/O study/O./O He/O turned/O over/O his/O stout/O,/O
well-cared-for/O person/O on/O the/O springy/O sofa/O,/O as/O though/O he/O would/O sink/O into/O
a/O long/O sleep/O again/O;/O he/O vigorously/O embraced/O the/O pillow/O on/O the/O other/O side/O
and/O buried/O his/O face/O in/O it/O;/O but/O all/O at/O once/O he/O jumped/O up/O,/O sat/O up/O on/O the/O
sofa/O,/O and/O opened/O his/O eyes/O./O

``/OYes/O,/O yes/O,/O how/O was/O it/O now/O?/O''/O he/O thought/O,/O going/O over/O his/O dream/O./O ``/ONow/O,/O how/O
was/O it/O?/O To/O be/O sure/O!/O Alabin/PERSON was/O giving/O a/O dinner/O at/O Darmstadt/LOCATION;/O no/O,/O not/O
Darmstadt/LOCATION,/O but/O something/O American/O./O Yes/O,/O but/O then/O,/O Darmstadt/LOCATION was/O in/O
America/LOCATION./O Yes/O,/O Alabin/PERSON was/O giving/O a/O dinner/O on/O glass/O tables/O,/O and/O the/O tables/O
sang/O,/O _/OIl/O mio/O tesoro/O_/O--/Onot/O _/OIl/O mio/O tesoro/O_/O though/O,/O but/O something/O better/O,/O
and/O there/O were/O some/O sort/O of/O little/O decanters/O on/O the/O table/O,/O and/O they/O were/O
women/O,/O too/O,/O''/O he/O remembered/O./O

Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON's/O eyes/O twinkled/O gaily/O,/O and/O he/O pondered/O with/O a/O smile/O./O
``/OYes/O,/O it/O was/O nice/O,/O very/O nice/O./O There/O was/O a/O great/O deal/O more/O that/O was/O
delightful/O,/O only/O there/O's/O no/O putting/O it/O into/O words/O,/O or/O even/O expressing/O it/O
in/O one/O's/O thoughts/O awake/O./O''/O And/O noticing/O a/O gleam/O of/O light/O peeping/O in/O
beside/O one/O of/O the/O serge/O curtains/O,/O he/O cheerfully/O dropped/O his/O feet/O over/O
the/O edge/O of/O the/O sofa/O,/O and/O felt/O about/O with/O them/O for/O his/O slippers/O,/O a/O
present/O on/O his/O last/O birthday/O,/O worked/O for/O him/O by/O his/O wife/O on/O gold-colored/O
morocco/O./O And/O,/O as/O he/O had/O done/O every/O day/O for/O the/O last/O nine/O years/O,/O he/O
stretched/O out/O his/O hand/O,/O without/O getting/O up/O,/O towards/O the/O place/O where/O his/O
dressing-gown/O always/O hung/O in/O his/O bedroom/O./O And/O thereupon/O he/O suddenly/O
remembered/O that/O he/O was/O not/O sleeping/O in/O his/O wife/O's/O room/O,/O but/O in/O his/O
study/O,/O and/O why/O:/O the/O smile/O vanished/O from/O his/O face/O,/O he/O knitted/O his/O brows/O./O

``/OAh/O,/O ah/O,/O ah/O!/O Oo/O!/O.../O''/O he/O muttered/O,/O recalling/O everything/O that/O had/O
happened/O./O And/O again/O every/O detail/O of/O his/O quarrel/O with/O his/O wife/O was/O
present/O to/O his/O imagination/O,/O all/O the/O hopelessness/O of/O his/O position/O,/O and/O
worst/O of/O all/O,/O his/O own/O fault/O./O

``/OYes/O,/O she/O wo/On't/O forgive/O me/O,/O and/O she/O ca/On't/O forgive/O me/O./O And/O the/O most/O awful/O
thing/O about/O it/O is/O that/O it/O's/O all/O my/O fault/O--/Oall/O my/O fault/O,/O though/O I/O'm/O not/O to/O
blame/O./O That/O's/O the/O point/O of/O the/O whole/O situation/O,/O''/O he/O reflected/O./O ``/OOh/O,/O oh/O,/O
oh/O!/O''/O he/O kept/O repeating/O in/O despair/O,/O as/O he/O remembered/O the/O acutely/O painful/O
sensations/O caused/O him/O by/O this/O quarrel/O./O

Most/O unpleasant/O of/O all/O was/O the/O first/O minute/O when/O,/O on/O coming/O,/O happy/O and/O
good-humored/O,/O from/O the/O theater/O,/O with/O a/O huge/O pear/O in/O his/O hand/O for/O his/O
wife/O,/O he/O had/O not/O found/O his/O wife/O in/O the/O drawing-room/O,/O to/O his/O surprise/O had/O
not/O found/O her/O in/O the/O study/O either/O,/O and/O saw/O her/O at/O last/O in/O her/O bedroom/O
with/O the/O unlucky/O letter/O that/O revealed/O everything/O in/O her/O hand/O./O

She/O,/O his/O Dolly/PERSON,/O forever/O fussing/O and/O worrying/O over/O household/O details/O,/O and/O
limited/O in/O her/O ideas/O,/O as/O he/O considered/O,/O was/O sitting/O perfectly/O still/O with/O
the/O letter/O in/O her/O hand/O,/O looking/O at/O him/O with/O an/O expression/O of/O horror/O,/O
despair/O,/O and/O indignation/O./O

``/OWhat/O's/O this/O?/O this/O?/O''/O she/O asked/O,/O pointing/O to/O the/O letter/O./O

And/O at/O this/O recollection/O,/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON,/O as/O is/O so/O often/O the/O case/O,/O
was/O not/O so/O much/O annoyed/O at/O the/O fact/O itself/O as/O at/O the/O way/O in/O which/O he/O had/O
met/O his/O wife/O's/O words/O./O

There/O happened/O to/O him/O at/O that/O instant/O what/O does/O happen/O to/O people/O when/O
they/O are/O unexpectedly/O caught/O in/O something/O very/O disgraceful/O./O He/O did/O not/O
succeed/O in/O adapting/O his/O face/O to/O the/O position/O in/O which/O he/O was/O placed/O
towards/O his/O wife/O by/O the/O discovery/O of/O his/O fault/O./O Instead/O of/O being/O hurt/O,/O
denying/O,/O defending/O himself/O,/O begging/O forgiveness/O,/O instead/O of/O remaining/O
indifferent/O even/O--/Oanything/O would/O have/O been/O better/O than/O what/O he/O did/O do/O--/Ohis/O
face/O utterly/O involuntarily/O -LRB-/Oreflex/O spinal/O action/O,/O reflected/O Stepan/PERSON
Arkadyevitch/PERSON,/O who/O was/O fond/O of/O physiology/O-RRB-/O--/Outterly/O involuntarily/O assumed/O
its/O habitual/O,/O good-humored/O,/O and/O therefore/O idiotic/O smile/O./O

This/O idiotic/O smile/O he/O could/O not/O forgive/O himself/O./O Catching/O sight/O of/O that/O
smile/O,/O Dolly/PERSON shuddered/O as/O though/O at/O physical/O pain/O,/O broke/O out/O with/O her/O
characteristic/O heat/O into/O a/O flood/O of/O cruel/O words/O,/O and/O rushed/O out/O of/O the/O
room/O./O Since/O then/O she/O had/O refused/O to/O see/O her/O husband/O./O

``/OIt/O's/O that/O idiotic/O smile/O that/O's/O to/O blame/O for/O it/O all/O,/O''/O thought/O Stepan/PERSON
Arkadyevitch/PERSON./O

``/OBut/O what/O's/O to/O be/O done/O?/O What/O's/O to/O be/O done/O?/O''/O he/O said/O to/O himself/O in/O
despair/O,/O and/O found/O no/O answer/O./O



Chapter/O 2/O


Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON was/O a/O truthful/O man/O in/O his/O relations/O with/O himself/O./O He/O
was/O incapable/O of/O deceiving/O himself/O and/O persuading/O himself/O that/O he/O
repented/O of/O his/O conduct/O./O He/O could/O not/O at/O this/O date/O repent/O of/O the/O fact/O
that/O he/O,/O a/O handsome/O,/O susceptible/O man/O of/O thirty-four/O,/O was/O not/O in/O love/O
with/O his/O wife/O,/O the/O mother/O of/O five/O living/O and/O two/O dead/O children/O,/O and/O only/O
a/O year/O younger/O than/O himself/O./O All/O he/O repented/O of/O was/O that/O he/O had/O not/O
succeeded/O better/O in/O hiding/O it/O from/O his/O wife/O./O But/O he/O felt/O all/O the/O
difficulty/O of/O his/O position/O and/O was/O sorry/O for/O his/O wife/O,/O his/O children/O,/O and/O
himself/O./O Possibly/O he/O might/O have/O managed/O to/O conceal/O his/O sins/O better/O from/O
his/O wife/O if/O he/O had/O anticipated/O that/O the/O knowledge/O of/O them/O would/O have/O had/O
such/O an/O effect/O on/O her/O./O He/O had/O never/O clearly/O thought/O out/O the/O subject/O,/O but/O
he/O had/O vaguely/O conceived/O that/O his/O wife/O must/O long/O ago/O have/O suspected/O him/O
of/O being/O unfaithful/O to/O her/O,/O and/O shut/O her/O eyes/O to/O the/O fact/O./O He/O had/O even/O
supposed/O that/O she/O,/O a/O worn-out/O woman/O no/O longer/O young/O or/O good-looking/O,/O and/O
in/O no/O way/O remarkable/O or/O interesting/O,/O merely/O a/O good/O mother/O,/O ought/O from/O a/O
sense/O of/O fairness/O to/O take/O an/O indulgent/O view/O./O It/O had/O turned/O out/O quite/O the/O
other/O way/O./O

``/OOh/O,/O it/O's/O awful/O!/O oh/O dear/O,/O oh/O dear/O!/O awful/O!/O''/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON kept/O
repeating/O to/O himself/O,/O and/O he/O could/O think/O of/O nothing/O to/O be/O done/O./O ``/OAnd/O how/O
well/O things/O were/O going/O up/O till/O now/O!/O how/O well/O we/O got/O on/O!/O She/O was/O
contented/O and/O happy/O in/O her/O children/O;/O I/O never/O interfered/O with/O her/O in/O
anything/O;/O I/O let/O her/O manage/O the/O children/O and/O the/O house/O just/O as/O she/O liked/O./O
It/O's/O true/O it/O's/O bad/O _/Oher/O_/O having/O been/O a/O governess/O in/O our/O house/O./O That/O's/O
bad/O!/O There/O's/O something/O common/O,/O vulgar/O,/O in/O flirting/O with/O one/O's/O governess/O./O
But/O what/O a/O governess/O!/O''/O -LRB-/OHe/O vividly/O recalled/O the/O roguish/O black/O eyes/O of/O
Mlle./O Roland/PERSON and/O her/O smile/O./O-RRB-/O ``/OBut/O after/O all/O,/O while/O she/O was/O in/O the/O house/O,/O
I/O kept/O myself/O in/O hand/O./O And/O the/O worst/O of/O it/O all/O is/O that/O she/O's/O already/O .../O
it/O seems/O as/O if/O ill-luck/O would/O have/O it/O so/O!/O Oh/O,/O oh/O!/O But/O what/O,/O what/O is/O to/O
be/O done/O?/O''/O

There/O was/O no/O solution/O,/O but/O that/O universal/O solution/O which/O life/O gives/O to/O
all/O questions/O,/O even/O the/O most/O complex/O and/O insoluble/O./O That/O answer/O is/O:/O one/O
must/O live/O in/O the/O needs/O of/O the/O day/O--/Othat/O is/O,/O forget/O oneself/O./O To/O forget/O
himself/O in/O sleep/O was/O impossible/O now/O,/O at/O least/O till/O nighttime/O;/O he/O could/O
not/O go/O back/O now/O to/O the/O music/O sung/O by/O the/O decanter-women/O;/O so/O he/O must/O
forget/O himself/O in/O the/O dream/O of/O daily/O life/O./O

``/OThen/O we/O shall/O see/O,/O''/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON said/O to/O himself/O,/O and/O getting/O up/O
he/O put/O on/O a/O gray/O dressing-gown/O lined/O with/O blue/O silk/O,/O tied/O the/O tassels/O in/O
a/O knot/O,/O and/O,/O drawing/O a/O deep/O breath/O of/O air/O into/O his/O broad/O,/O bare/O chest/O,/O he/O
walked/O to/O the/O window/O with/O his/O usual/O confident/O step/O,/O turning/O out/O his/O feet/O
that/O carried/O his/O full/O frame/O so/O easily/O./O He/O pulled/O up/O the/O blind/O and/O rang/O
the/O bell/O loudly/O./O It/O was/O at/O once/O answered/O by/O the/O appearance/O of/O an/O old/O
friend/O,/O his/O valet/O,/O Matvey/PERSON,/O carrying/O his/O clothes/O,/O his/O boots/O,/O and/O a/O
telegram/O./O Matvey/PERSON was/O followed/O by/O the/O barber/O with/O all/O the/O necessaries/O for/O
shaving/O./O

``/OAre/O there/O any/O papers/O from/O the/O office/O?/O''/O asked/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON,/O
taking/O the/O telegram/O and/O seating/O himself/O at/O the/O looking-glass/O./O

``/OOn/O the/O table/O,/O''/O replied/O Matvey/PERSON,/O glancing/O with/O inquiring/O sympathy/O at/O his/O
master/O;/O and/O,/O after/O a/O short/O pause/O,/O he/O added/O with/O a/O sly/O smile/O,/O ``/OThey/O've/O
sent/O from/O the/O carriage-jobbers/O./O''/O

Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON made/O no/O reply/O,/O he/O merely/O glanced/O at/O Matvey/LOCATION in/O the/O
looking-glass/O./O In/O the/O glance/O,/O in/O which/O their/O eyes/O met/O in/O the/O
looking-glass/O,/O it/O was/O clear/O that/O they/O understood/O one/O another/O./O Stepan/PERSON
Arkadyevitch/PERSON's/O eyes/O asked/O:/O ``/OWhy/O do/O you/O tell/O me/O that/O?/O do/On't/O you/O know/O?/O''/O

Matvey/PERSON put/O his/O hands/O in/O his/O jacket/O pockets/O,/O thrust/O out/O one/O leg/O,/O and/O
gazed/O silently/O,/O good-humoredly/O,/O with/O a/O faint/O smile/O,/O at/O his/O master/O./O

``/OI/O told/O them/O to/O come/O on/O Sunday/O,/O and/O till/O then/O not/O to/O trouble/O you/O or/O
themselves/O for/O nothing/O,/O''/O he/O said/O./O He/O had/O obviously/O prepared/O the/O sentence/O
beforehand/O./O

Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON saw/O Matvey/PERSON wanted/O to/O make/O a/O joke/O and/O attract/O
attention/O to/O himself/O./O Tearing/O open/O the/O telegram/O,/O he/O read/O it/O through/O,/O
guessing/O at/O the/O words/O,/O misspelt/O as/O they/O always/O are/O in/O telegrams/O,/O and/O his/O
face/O brightened/O./O

``/OMatvey/PERSON,/O my/O sister/O Anna/PERSON Arkadyevna/PERSON will/O be/O here/O tomorrow/O,/O''/O he/O said/O,/O
checking/O for/O a/O minute/O the/O sleek/O,/O plump/O hand/O of/O the/O barber/O,/O cutting/O a/O
pink/O path/O through/O his/O long/O,/O curly/O whiskers/O./O

``/OThank/O God/O!/O''/O said/O Matvey/PERSON,/O showing/O by/O this/O response/O that/O he/O,/O like/O his/O
master/O,/O realized/O the/O significance/O of/O this/O arrival/O--/Othat/O is/O,/O that/O Anna/PERSON
Arkadyevna/PERSON,/O the/O sister/O he/O was/O so/O fond/O of/O,/O might/O bring/O about/O a/O
reconciliation/O between/O husband/O and/O wife/O./O

``/OAlone/O,/O or/O with/O her/O husband/O?/O''/O inquired/O Matvey/PERSON./O

Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON could/O not/O answer/O,/O as/O the/O barber/O was/O at/O work/O on/O his/O
upper/O lip/O,/O and/O he/O raised/O one/O finger/O./O Matvey/PERSON nodded/O at/O the/O looking-glass/O./O

``/OAlone/O./O Is/O the/O room/O to/O be/O got/O ready/O upstairs/O?/O''/O

``/OInform/O Darya/PERSON Alexandrovna/PERSON:/O where/O she/O orders/O./O''/O

``/ODarya/PERSON Alexandrovna/PERSON?/O''/O Matvey/O repeated/O,/O as/O though/O in/O doubt/O./O

``/OYes/O,/O inform/O her/O./O Here/O,/O take/O the/O telegram/O;/O give/O it/O to/O her/O,/O and/O then/O do/O
what/O she/O tells/O you/O./O''/O

``/OYou/O want/O to/O try/O it/O on/O,/O''/O Matvey/PERSON understood/O,/O but/O he/O only/O said/O,/O ``/OYes/O sir/O./O''/O

Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON was/O already/O washed/O and/O combed/O and/O ready/O to/O be/O
dressed/O,/O when/O Matvey/PERSON,/O stepping/O deliberately/O in/O his/O creaky/O boots/O,/O came/O
back/O into/O the/O room/O with/O the/O telegram/O in/O his/O hand/O./O The/O barber/O had/O gone/O./O

``/ODarya/PERSON Alexandrovna/PERSON told/O me/O to/O inform/O you/O that/O she/O is/O going/O away/O./O Let/O
him/O do/O--/Othat/O is/O you/O--/Odo/O as/O he/O likes/O,/O''/O he/O said/O,/O laughing/O only/O with/O his/O
eyes/O,/O and/O putting/O his/O hands/O in/O his/O pockets/O,/O he/O watched/O his/O master/O with/O
his/O head/O on/O one/O side/O./O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON was/O silent/O a/O minute/O./O Then/O a/O
good-humored/O and/O rather/O pitiful/O smile/O showed/O itself/O on/O his/O handsome/O
face/O./O

``/OEh/O,/O Matvey/PERSON?/O''/O he/O said/O,/O shaking/O his/O head/O./O

``/OIt/O's/O all/O right/O,/O sir/O;/O she/O will/O come/O round/O,/O''/O said/O Matvey/PERSON./O

``/OCome/O round/O?/O''/O

``/OYes/O,/O sir/O./O''/O

``/ODo/O you/O think/O so/O?/O Who/O's/O there/O?/O''/O asked/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON,/O hearing/O the/O
rustle/O of/O a/O woman/O's/O dress/O at/O the/O door/O./O

``/OIt/O's/O I/O,/O''/O said/O a/O firm/O,/O pleasant/O,/O woman/O's/O voice/O,/O and/O the/O stern/O,/O
pockmarked/O face/O of/O Matrona/PERSON Philimonovna/PERSON,/O the/O nurse/O,/O was/O thrust/O in/O at/O the/O
doorway/O./O

``/OWell/O,/O what/O is/O it/O,/O Matrona/PERSON?/O''/O queried/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON,/O going/O up/O to/O
her/O at/O the/O door/O./O

Although/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON was/O completely/O in/O the/O wrong/O as/O regards/O his/O
wife/O,/O and/O was/O conscious/O of/O this/O himself/O,/O almost/O every/O one/O in/O the/O house/O
-LRB-/Oeven/O the/O nurse/O,/O Darya/PERSON Alexandrovna/PERSON's/O chief/O ally/O-RRB-/O was/O on/O his/O side/O./O

``/OWell/O,/O what/O now/O?/O''/O he/O asked/O disconsolately/O./O

``/OGo/O to/O her/O,/O sir/O;/O own/O your/O fault/O again/O./O Maybe/O God/O will/O aid/O you/O./O She/O is/O
suffering/O so/O,/O it/O's/O sad/O to/O see/O her/O;/O and/O besides/O,/O everything/O in/O the/O house/O
is/O topsy-turvy/O./O You/O must/O have/O pity/O,/O sir/O,/O on/O the/O children/O./O Beg/O her/O
forgiveness/O,/O sir/O./O There/O's/O no/O help/O for/O it/O!/O One/O must/O take/O the/O
consequences/O.../O''/O

``/OBut/O she/O wo/On't/O see/O me/O./O''/O

``/OYou/O do/O your/O part/O./O God/O is/O merciful/O;/O pray/O to/O God/O,/O sir/O,/O pray/O to/O God/O./O''/O

``/OCome/O,/O that/O'll/O do/O,/O you/O can/O go/O,/O''/O said/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON,/O blushing/O
suddenly/O./O ``/OWell/O now/O,/O do/O dress/O me/O./O''/O He/O turned/O to/O Matvey/PERSON and/O threw/O off/O his/O
dressing-gown/O decisively/O./O

Matvey/PERSON was/O already/O holding/O up/O the/O shirt/O like/O a/O horse/O's/O collar/O,/O and/O,/O
blowing/O off/O some/O invisible/O speck/O,/O he/O slipped/O it/O with/O obvious/O pleasure/O
over/O the/O well-groomed/O body/O of/O his/O master/O./O



Chapter/O 3/O


When/O he/O was/O dressed/O,/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON sprinkled/O some/O scent/O on/O
himself/O,/O pulled/O down/O his/O shirt-cuffs/O,/O distributed/O into/O his/O pockets/O his/O
cigarettes/O,/O pocketbook/O,/O matches/O,/O and/O watch/O with/O its/O double/O chain/O and/O
seals/O,/O and/O shaking/O out/O his/O handkerchief/O,/O feeling/O himself/O clean/O,/O
fragrant/O,/O healthy/O,/O and/O physically/O at/O ease/O,/O in/O spite/O of/O his/O unhappiness/O,/O
he/O walked/O with/O a/O slight/O swing/O on/O each/O leg/O into/O the/O dining-room/O,/O where/O
coffee/O was/O already/O waiting/O for/O him/O,/O and/O beside/O the/O coffee/O,/O letters/O and/O
papers/O from/O the/O office/O./O

He/O read/O the/O letters/O./O One/O was/O very/O unpleasant/O,/O from/O a/O merchant/O who/O was/O
buying/O a/O forest/O on/O his/O wife/O's/O property/O./O To/O sell/O this/O forest/O was/O
absolutely/O essential/O;/O but/O at/O present/O,/O until/O he/O was/O reconciled/O with/O his/O
wife/O,/O the/O subject/O could/O not/O be/O discussed/O./O The/O most/O unpleasant/O thing/O of/O
all/O was/O that/O his/O pecuniary/O interests/O should/O in/O this/O way/O enter/O into/O the/O
question/O of/O his/O reconciliation/O with/O his/O wife/O./O And/O the/O idea/O that/O he/O might/O
be/O led/O on/O by/O his/O interests/O,/O that/O he/O might/O seek/O a/O reconciliation/O with/O his/O
wife/O on/O account/O of/O the/O sale/O of/O the/O forest/O--/Othat/O idea/O hurt/O him/O./O

When/O he/O had/O finished/O his/O letters/O,/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON moved/O the/O
office-papers/O close/O to/O him/O,/O rapidly/O looked/O through/O two/O pieces/O of/O
business/O,/O made/O a/O few/O notes/O with/O a/O big/O pencil/O,/O and/O pushing/O away/O the/O
papers/O,/O turned/O to/O his/O coffee/O./O As/O he/O sipped/O his/O coffee/O,/O he/O opened/O a/O still/O
damp/O morning/O paper/O,/O and/O began/O reading/O it/O./O

Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON took/O in/O and/O read/O a/O liberal/O paper/O,/O not/O an/O extreme/O
one/O,/O but/O one/O advocating/O the/O views/O held/O by/O the/O majority/O./O And/O in/O spite/O of/O
the/O fact/O that/O science/O,/O art/O,/O and/O politics/O had/O no/O special/O interest/O for/O
him/O,/O he/O firmly/O held/O those/O views/O on/O all/O these/O subjects/O which/O were/O held/O by/O
the/O majority/O and/O by/O his/O paper/O,/O and/O he/O only/O changed/O them/O when/O the/O
majority/O changed/O them/O--/Oor/O,/O more/O strictly/O speaking/O,/O he/O did/O not/O change/O
them/O,/O but/O they/O imperceptibly/O changed/O of/O themselves/O within/O him/O./O

Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON had/O not/O chosen/O his/O political/O opinions/O or/O his/O views/O;/O
these/O political/O opinions/O and/O views/O had/O come/O to/O him/O of/O themselves/O,/O just/O
as/O he/O did/O not/O choose/O the/O shapes/O of/O his/O hat/O and/O coat/O,/O but/O simply/O took/O
those/O that/O were/O being/O worn/O./O And/O for/O him/O,/O living/O in/O a/O certain/O
society/O--/Oowing/O to/O the/O need/O,/O ordinarily/O developed/O at/O years/O of/O discretion/O,/O
for/O some/O degree/O of/O mental/O activity/O--/Oto/O have/O views/O was/O just/O as/O
indispensable/O as/O to/O have/O a/O hat/O./O If/O there/O was/O a/O reason/O for/O his/O preferring/O
liberal/O to/O conservative/O views/O,/O which/O were/O held/O also/O by/O many/O of/O his/O
circle/O,/O it/O arose/O not/O from/O his/O considering/O liberalism/O more/O rational/O,/O but/O
from/O its/O being/O in/O closer/O accordance/O with/O his/O manner/O of/O life/O./O The/O liberal/O
party/O said/O that/O in/O Russia/LOCATION everything/O is/O wrong/O,/O and/O certainly/O Stepan/PERSON
Arkadyevitch/PERSON had/O many/O debts/O and/O was/O decidedly/O short/O of/O money/O./O The/O
liberal/O party/O said/O that/O marriage/O is/O an/O institution/O quite/O out/O of/O date/O,/O
and/O that/O it/O needs/O reconstruction/O;/O and/O family/O life/O certainly/O afforded/O
Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON little/O gratification/O,/O and/O forced/O him/O into/O lying/O and/O
hypocrisy/O,/O which/O was/O so/O repulsive/O to/O his/O nature/O./O The/O liberal/O party/O said/O,/O
or/O rather/O allowed/O it/O to/O be/O understood/O,/O that/O religion/O is/O only/O a/O curb/O to/O
keep/O in/O check/O the/O barbarous/O classes/O of/O the/O people/O;/O and/O Stepan/PERSON
Arkadyevitch/PERSON could/O not/O get/O through/O even/O a/O short/O service/O without/O his/O legs/O
aching/O from/O standing/O up/O,/O and/O could/O never/O make/O out/O what/O was/O the/O object/O of/O
all/O the/O terrible/O and/O high-flown/O language/O about/O another/O world/O when/O life/O
might/O be/O so/O very/O amusing/O in/O this/O world/O./O And/O with/O all/O this/O,/O Stepan/PERSON
Arkadyevitch/PERSON,/O who/O liked/O a/O joke/O,/O was/O fond/O of/O puzzling/O a/O plain/O man/O by/O
saying/O that/O if/O he/O prided/O himself/O on/O his/O origin/O,/O he/O ought/O not/O to/O stop/O at/O
Rurik/LOCATION and/O disown/O the/O first/O founder/O of/O his/O family/O--/Othe/O monkey/O./O And/O so/O
Liberalism/O had/O become/O a/O habit/O of/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON's/O,/O and/O he/O liked/O his/O
newspaper/O,/O as/O he/O did/O his/O cigar/O after/O dinner/O,/O for/O the/O slight/O fog/O it/O
diffused/O in/O his/O brain/O./O He/O read/O the/O leading/O article/O,/O in/O which/O it/O was/O
maintained/O that/O it/O was/O quite/O senseless/O in/O our/O day/O to/O raise/O an/O outcry/O
that/O radicalism/O was/O threatening/O to/O swallow/O up/O all/O conservative/O elements/O,/O
and/O that/O the/O government/O ought/O to/O take/O measures/O to/O crush/O the/O
revolutionary/O hydra/O;/O that/O,/O on/O the/O contrary/O,/O ``/Oin/O our/O opinion/O the/O danger/O
lies/O not/O in/O that/O fantastic/O revolutionary/O hydra/O,/O but/O in/O the/O obstinacy/O of/O
traditionalism/O clogging/O progress/O,/O''/O etc./O,/O etc./O./O He/O read/O another/O article/O,/O
too/O,/O a/O financial/O one/O,/O which/O alluded/O to/O Bentham/PERSON and/O Mill/O,/O and/O dropped/O
some/O innuendoes/O reflecting/O on/O the/O ministry/O./O With/O his/O characteristic/O
quickwittedness/O he/O caught/O the/O drift/O of/O each/O innuendo/O,/O divined/O whence/O it/O
came/O,/O at/O whom/O and/O on/O what/O ground/O it/O was/O aimed/O,/O and/O that/O afforded/O him/O,/O as/O
it/O always/O did/O,/O a/O certain/O satisfaction/O./O But/O today/O that/O satisfaction/O was/O
embittered/O by/O Matrona/PERSON Philimonovna/PERSON's/O advice/O and/O the/O unsatisfactory/O state/O
of/O the/O household/O./O He/O read/O,/O too/O,/O that/O Count/O Beist/PERSON was/O rumored/O to/O have/O
left/O for/O Wiesbaden/LOCATION,/O and/O that/O one/O need/O have/O no/O more/O gray/O hair/O,/O and/O of/O the/O
sale/O of/O a/O light/O carriage/O,/O and/O of/O a/O young/O person/O seeking/O a/O situation/O;/O but/O
these/O items/O of/O information/O did/O not/O give/O him/O,/O as/O usual/O,/O a/O quiet/O,/O ironical/O
gratification/O./O Having/O finished/O the/O paper/O,/O a/O second/O cup/O of/O coffee/O and/O a/O
roll/O and/O butter/O,/O he/O got/O up/O,/O shaking/O the/O crumbs/O of/O the/O roll/O off/O his/O
waistcoat/O;/O and/O,/O squaring/O his/O broad/O chest/O,/O he/O smiled/O joyously/O:/O not/O
because/O there/O was/O anything/O particularly/O agreeable/O in/O his/O mind/O--/Othe/O joyous/O
smile/O was/O evoked/O by/O a/O good/O digestion/O./O

But/O this/O joyous/O smile/O at/O once/O recalled/O everything/O to/O him/O,/O and/O he/O grew/O
thoughtful/O./O

Two/O childish/O voices/O -LRB-/OStepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON recognized/O the/O voices/O of/O
Grisha/PERSON,/O his/O youngest/O boy/O,/O and/O Tanya/PERSON,/O his/O eldest/O girl/O-RRB-/O were/O heard/O outside/O
the/O door/O./O They/O were/O carrying/O something/O,/O and/O dropped/O it/O./O

``/OI/O told/O you/O not/O to/O sit/O passengers/O on/O the/O roof/O,/O''/O said/O the/O little/O girl/O in/O
English/O;/O ``/Othere/O,/O pick/O them/O up/O!/O''/O

``/OEverything/O's/O in/O confusion/O,/O''/O thought/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON;/O ``/Othere/O are/O the/O
children/O running/O about/O by/O themselves/O./O''/O And/O going/O to/O the/O door/O,/O he/O called/O
them/O./O They/O threw/O down/O the/O box/O,/O that/O represented/O a/O train/O,/O and/O came/O in/O to/O
their/O father/O./O

The/O little/O girl/O,/O her/O father/O's/O favorite/O,/O ran/O up/O boldly/O,/O embraced/O him/O,/O and/O
hung/O laughingly/O on/O his/O neck/O,/O enjoying/O as/O she/O always/O did/O the/O smell/O of/O
scent/O that/O came/O from/O his/O whiskers/O./O At/O last/O the/O little/O girl/O kissed/O his/O
face/O,/O which/O was/O flushed/O from/O his/O stooping/O posture/O and/O beaming/O with/O
tenderness/O,/O loosed/O her/O hands/O,/O and/O was/O about/O to/O run/O away/O again/O;/O but/O her/O
father/O held/O her/O back/O./O

``/OHow/O is/O mamma/O?/O''/O he/O asked/O,/O passing/O his/O hand/O over/O his/O daughter/O's/O smooth/O,/O
soft/O little/O neck/O./O ``/OGood/O morning/O,/O''/O he/O said/O,/O smiling/O to/O the/O boy/O,/O who/O had/O
come/O up/O to/O greet/O him/O./O He/O was/O conscious/O that/O he/O loved/O the/O boy/O less/O,/O and/O
always/O tried/O to/O be/O fair/O;/O but/O the/O boy/O felt/O it/O,/O and/O did/O not/O respond/O with/O a/O
smile/O to/O his/O father/O's/O chilly/O smile/O./O

``/OMamma/O?/O She/O is/O up/O,/O''/O answered/O the/O girl/O./O

Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON sighed/O./O ``/OThat/O means/O that/O she/O's/O not/O slept/O again/O all/O
night/O,/O''/O he/O thought/O./O

``/OWell/O,/O is/O she/O cheerful/O?/O''/O

The/O little/O girl/O knew/O that/O there/O was/O a/O quarrel/O between/O her/O father/O and/O
mother/O,/O and/O that/O her/O mother/O could/O not/O be/O cheerful/O,/O and/O that/O her/O father/O
must/O be/O aware/O of/O this/O,/O and/O that/O he/O was/O pretending/O when/O he/O asked/O about/O it/O
so/O lightly/O./O And/O she/O blushed/O for/O her/O father/O./O He/O at/O once/O perceived/O it/O,/O and/O
blushed/O too/O./O

``/OI/O do/On't/O know/O,/O''/O she/O said/O./O ``/OShe/O did/O not/O say/O we/O must/O do/O our/O lessons/O,/O but/O
she/O said/O we/O were/O to/O go/O for/O a/O walk/O with/O Miss/O Hoole/PERSON to/O grandmamma/O's/O./O''/O

``/OWell/O,/O go/O,/O Tanya/PERSON,/O my/O darling/O./O Oh/O,/O wait/O a/O minute/O,/O though/O,/O''/O he/O said/O,/O still/O
holding/O her/O and/O stroking/O her/O soft/O little/O hand/O./O

He/O took/O off/O the/O mantelpiece/O,/O where/O he/O had/O put/O it/O yesterday/O,/O a/O little/O box/O
of/O sweets/O,/O and/O gave/O her/O two/O,/O picking/O out/O her/O favorites/O,/O a/O chocolate/O and/O
a/O fondant/O./O

``/OFor/O Grisha/PERSON?/O''/O said/O the/O little/O girl/O,/O pointing/O to/O the/O chocolate/O./O

``/OYes/O,/O yes/O./O''/O And/O still/O stroking/O her/O little/O shoulder/O,/O he/O kissed/O her/O on/O the/O
roots/O of/O her/O hair/O and/O neck/O,/O and/O let/O her/O go/O./O

``/OThe/O carriage/O is/O ready/O,/O''/O said/O Matvey/PERSON;/O ``/Obut/O there/O's/O some/O one/O to/O see/O you/O
with/O a/O petition/O./O''/O

``/OBeen/O here/O long/O?/O''/O asked/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON./O

``/OHalf/O an/O hour/O./O''/O

``/OHow/O many/O times/O have/O I/O told/O you/O to/O tell/O me/O at/O once/O?/O''/O

``/OOne/O must/O let/O you/O drink/O your/O coffee/O in/O peace/O,/O at/O least/O,/O''/O said/O Matvey/PERSON,/O in/O
the/O affectionately/O gruff/O tone/O with/O which/O it/O was/O impossible/O to/O be/O angry/O./O

``/OWell/O,/O show/O the/O person/O up/O at/O once/O,/O''/O said/O Oblonsky/PERSON,/O frowning/O with/O
vexation/O./O

The/O petitioner/O,/O the/O widow/O of/O a/O staff/O captain/O Kalinin/PERSON,/O came/O with/O a/O
request/O impossible/O and/O unreasonable/O;/O but/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON,/O as/O he/O
generally/O did/O,/O made/O her/O sit/O down/O,/O heard/O her/O to/O the/O end/O attentively/O
without/O interrupting/O her/O,/O and/O gave/O her/O detailed/O advice/O as/O to/O how/O and/O to/O
whom/O to/O apply/O,/O and/O even/O wrote/O her/O,/O in/O his/O large/O,/O sprawling/O,/O good/O and/O
legible/O hand/O,/O a/O confident/O and/O fluent/O little/O note/O to/O a/O personage/O who/O
might/O be/O of/O use/O to/O her/O./O Having/O got/O rid/O of/O the/O staff/O captain/O's/O widow/O,/O
Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON took/O his/O hat/O and/O stopped/O to/O recollect/O whether/O he/O had/O
forgotten/O anything/O./O It/O appeared/O that/O he/O had/O forgotten/O nothing/O except/O
what/O he/O wanted/O to/O forget/O--/Ohis/O wife/O./O

``/OAh/O,/O yes/O!/O''/O He/O bowed/O his/O head/O,/O and/O his/O handsome/O face/O assumed/O a/O harassed/O
expression/O./O ``/OTo/O go/O,/O or/O not/O to/O go/O!/O''/O he/O said/O to/O himself/O;/O and/O an/O inner/O
voice/O told/O him/O he/O must/O not/O go/O,/O that/O nothing/O could/O come/O of/O it/O but/O
falsity/O;/O that/O to/O amend/O,/O to/O set/O right/O their/O relations/O was/O impossible/O,/O
because/O it/O was/O impossible/O to/O make/O her/O attractive/O again/O and/O able/O to/O
inspire/O love/O,/O or/O to/O make/O him/O an/O old/O man/O,/O not/O susceptible/O to/O love/O./O Except/O
deceit/O and/O lying/O nothing/O could/O come/O of/O it/O now/O;/O and/O deceit/O and/O lying/O were/O
opposed/O to/O his/O nature/O./O

``/OIt/O must/O be/O some/O time/O,/O though/O:/O it/O ca/On't/O go/O on/O like/O this/O,/O''/O he/O said/O,/O
trying/O to/O give/O himself/O courage/O./O He/O squared/O his/O chest/O,/O took/O out/O a/O
cigarette/O,/O took/O two/O whiffs/O at/O it/O,/O flung/O it/O into/O a/O mother-of-pearl/O
ashtray/O,/O and/O with/O rapid/O steps/O walked/O through/O the/O drawing/O room/O,/O and/O
opened/O the/O other/O door/O into/O his/O wife/O's/O bedroom/O./O



Chapter/O 4/O


Darya/PERSON Alexandrovna/PERSON,/O in/O a/O dressing/O jacket/O,/O and/O with/O her/O now/O scanty/O,/O once/O
luxuriant/O and/O beautiful/O hair/O fastened/O up/O with/O hairpins/O on/O the/O nape/O of/O
her/O neck/O,/O with/O a/O sunken/O,/O thin/O face/O and/O large/O,/O startled/O eyes/O,/O which/O
looked/O prominent/O from/O the/O thinness/O of/O her/O face/O,/O was/O standing/O among/O a/O
litter/O of/O all/O sorts/O of/O things/O scattered/O all/O over/O the/O room/O,/O before/O an/O
open/O bureau/O,/O from/O which/O she/O was/O taking/O something/O./O Hearing/O her/O husband/O's/O
steps/O,/O she/O stopped/O,/O looking/O towards/O the/O door/O,/O and/O trying/O assiduously/O to/O
give/O her/O features/O a/O severe/O and/O contemptuous/O expression/O./O She/O felt/O she/O was/O
afraid/O of/O him/O,/O and/O afraid/O of/O the/O coming/O interview/O./O She/O was/O just/O
attempting/O to/O do/O what/O she/O had/O attempted/O to/O do/O ten/O times/O already/O in/O these/O
last/O three/O days/O--/Oto/O sort/O out/O the/O children/O's/O things/O and/O her/O own/O,/O so/O as/O to/O
take/O them/O to/O her/O mother/O's/O--/Oand/O again/O she/O could/O not/O bring/O herself/O to/O do/O
this/O;/O but/O now/O again/O,/O as/O each/O time/O before/O,/O she/O kept/O saying/O to/O herself/O,/O
``/Othat/O things/O can/Onot/O go/O on/O like/O this/O,/O that/O she/O must/O take/O some/O step/O''/O to/O
punish/O him/O,/O put/O him/O to/O shame/O,/O avenge/O on/O him/O some/O little/O part/O at/O least/O of/O
the/O suffering/O he/O had/O caused/O her/O./O She/O still/O continued/O to/O tell/O herself/O
that/O she/O should/O leave/O him/O,/O but/O she/O was/O conscious/O that/O this/O was/O
impossible/O;/O it/O was/O impossible/O because/O she/O could/O not/O get/O out/O of/O the/O habit/O
of/O regarding/O him/O as/O her/O husband/O and/O loving/O him/O./O Besides/O this/O,/O she/O
realized/O that/O if/O even/O here/O in/O her/O own/O house/O she/O could/O hardly/O manage/O to/O
look/O after/O her/O five/O children/O properly/O,/O they/O would/O be/O still/O worse/O off/O
where/O she/O was/O going/O with/O them/O all/O./O As/O it/O was/O,/O even/O in/O the/O course/O of/O
these/O three/O days/O,/O the/O youngest/O was/O unwell/O from/O being/O given/O unwholesome/O
soup/O,/O and/O the/O others/O had/O almost/O gone/O without/O their/O dinner/O the/O day/O
before/O./O She/O was/O conscious/O that/O it/O was/O impossible/O to/O go/O away/O;/O but/O,/O
cheating/O herself/O,/O she/O went/O on/O all/O the/O same/O sorting/O out/O her/O things/O and/O
pretending/O she/O was/O going/O./O

Seeing/O her/O husband/O,/O she/O dropped/O her/O hands/O into/O the/O drawer/O of/O the/O bureau/O
as/O though/O looking/O for/O something/O,/O and/O only/O looked/O round/O at/O him/O when/O he/O
had/O come/O quite/O up/O to/O her/O./O But/O her/O face/O,/O to/O which/O she/O tried/O to/O give/O a/O
severe/O and/O resolute/O expression/O,/O betrayed/O bewilderment/O and/O suffering/O./O

``/ODolly/O!/O''/O he/O said/O in/O a/O subdued/O and/O timid/O voice/O./O He/O bent/O his/O head/O towards/O
his/O shoulder/O and/O tried/O to/O look/O pitiful/O and/O humble/O,/O but/O for/O all/O that/O he/O
was/O radiant/O with/O freshness/O and/O health/O./O In/O a/O rapid/O glance/O she/O scanned/O his/O
figure/O that/O beamed/O with/O health/O and/O freshness/O./O ``/OYes/O,/O he/O is/O happy/O and/O
content/O!/O''/O she/O thought/O;/O ``/Owhile/O I./O.../O And/O that/O disgusting/O good/O nature/O,/O
which/O every/O one/O likes/O him/O for/O and/O praises/O--/OI/O hate/O that/O good/O nature/O of/O
his/O,/O''/O she/O thought/O./O Her/O mouth/O stiffened/O,/O the/O muscles/O of/O the/O cheek/O
contracted/O on/O the/O right/O side/O of/O her/O pale/O,/O nervous/O face/O./O

``/OWhat/O do/O you/O want/O?/O''/O she/O said/O in/O a/O rapid/O,/O deep/O,/O unnatural/O voice/O./O

``/ODolly/O!/O''/O he/O repeated/O,/O with/O a/O quiver/O in/O his/O voice/O./O ``/OAnna/PERSON is/O coming/O
today/O./O''/O

``/OWell/O,/O what/O is/O that/O to/O me/O?/O I/O ca/On't/O see/O her/O!/O''/O she/O cried/O./O

``/OBut/O you/O must/O,/O really/O,/O Dolly/PERSON.../O''/O

``/OGo/O away/O,/O go/O away/O,/O go/O away/O!/O''/O she/O shrieked/O,/O not/O looking/O at/O him/O,/O as/O though/O
this/O shriek/O were/O called/O up/O by/O physical/O pain/O./O

Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON could/O be/O calm/O when/O he/O thought/O of/O his/O wife/O,/O he/O could/O
hope/O that/O she/O would/O _/Ocome/O round/O_/O,/O as/O Matvey/PERSON expressed/O it/O,/O and/O could/O
quietly/O go/O on/O reading/O his/O paper/O and/O drinking/O his/O coffee/O;/O but/O when/O he/O saw/O
her/O tortured/O,/O suffering/O face/O,/O heard/O the/O tone/O of/O her/O voice/O,/O submissive/O to/O
fate/O and/O full/O of/O despair/O,/O there/O was/O a/O catch/O in/O his/O breath/O and/O a/O lump/O in/O
his/O throat/O,/O and/O his/O eyes/O began/O to/O shine/O with/O tears/O./O

``/OMy/O God/O!/O what/O have/O I/O done/O?/O Dolly/O!/O For/O God/O's/O sake/O!/O.../O./O You/O know/O.../O''/O He/O
could/O not/O go/O on/O;/O there/O was/O a/O sob/O in/O his/O throat/O./O

She/O shut/O the/O bureau/O with/O a/O slam/O,/O and/O glanced/O at/O him/O./O

``/ODolly/O,/O what/O can/O I/O say/O?/O.../O./O One/O thing/O:/O forgive/O.../O Remember/O,/O can/Onot/O nine/O
years/O of/O my/O life/O atone/O for/O an/O instant/O.../O''/O

She/O dropped/O her/O eyes/O and/O listened/O,/O expecting/O what/O he/O would/O say/O,/O as/O it/O
were/O beseeching/O him/O in/O some/O way/O or/O other/O to/O make/O her/O believe/O
differently/O./O

''/O--/Oinstant/O of/O passion/O?/O''/O he/O said/O,/O and/O would/O have/O gone/O on/O,/O but/O at/O that/O
word/O,/O as/O at/O a/O pang/O of/O physical/O pain/O,/O her/O lips/O stiffened/O again/O,/O and/O again/O
the/O muscles/O of/O her/O right/O cheek/O worked/O./O

``/OGo/O away/O,/O go/O out/O of/O the/O room/O!/O''/O she/O shrieked/O still/O more/O shrilly/O,/O ``/Oand/O
do/On't/O talk/O to/O me/O of/O your/O passion/O and/O your/O loathsomeness/O./O''/O

She/O tried/O to/O go/O out/O,/O but/O tottered/O,/O and/O clung/O to/O the/O back/O of/O a/O chair/O to/O
support/O herself/O./O His/O face/O relaxed/O,/O his/O lips/O swelled/O,/O his/O eyes/O were/O
swimming/O with/O tears/O./O

``/ODolly/O!/O''/O he/O said/O,/O sobbing/O now/O;/O ``/Ofor/O mercy/O's/O sake/O,/O think/O of/O the/O children/O;/O
they/O are/O not/O to/O blame/O!/O I/O am/O to/O blame/O,/O and/O punish/O me/O,/O make/O me/O expiate/O my/O
fault/O./O Anything/O I/O can/O do/O,/O I/O am/O ready/O to/O do/O anything/O!/O I/O am/O to/O blame/O,/O no/O
words/O can/O express/O how/O much/O I/O am/O to/O blame/O!/O But/O,/O Dolly/PERSON,/O forgive/O me/O!/O''/O

She/O sat/O down/O./O He/O listened/O to/O her/O hard/O,/O heavy/O breathing/O,/O and/O he/O was/O
unutterably/O sorry/O for/O her/O./O She/O tried/O several/O times/O to/O begin/O to/O speak/O,/O
but/O could/O not/O./O He/O waited/O./O

``/OYou/O remember/O the/O children/O,/O Stiva/PERSON,/O to/O play/O with/O them/O;/O but/O I/O remember/O
them/O,/O and/O know/O that/O this/O means/O their/O ruin/O,/O''/O she/O said/O--/Oobviously/O one/O of/O
the/O phrases/O she/O had/O more/O than/O once/O repeated/O to/O herself/O in/O the/O course/O of/O
the/O last/O few/O days/O./O

She/O had/O called/O him/O ``/OStiva/O,/O''/O and/O he/O glanced/O at/O her/O with/O gratitude/O,/O and/O
moved/O to/O take/O her/O hand/O,/O but/O she/O drew/O back/O from/O him/O with/O aversion/O./O

``/OI/O think/O of/O the/O children/O,/O and/O for/O that/O reason/O I/O would/O do/O anything/O in/O the/O
world/O to/O save/O them/O,/O but/O I/O do/On't/O myself/O know/O how/O to/O save/O them/O./O By/O taking/O
them/O away/O from/O their/O father/O,/O or/O by/O leaving/O them/O with/O a/O vicious/O
father/O--/Oyes/O,/O a/O vicious/O father/O.../O./O Tell/O me/O,/O after/O what/O .../O has/O happened/O,/O
can/O we/O live/O together/O?/O Is/O that/O possible/O?/O Tell/O me/O,/O eh/O,/O is/O it/O possible/O?/O''/O
she/O repeated/O,/O raising/O her/O voice/O,/O ``/Oafter/O my/O husband/O,/O the/O father/O of/O my/O
children/O,/O enters/O into/O a/O love/O affair/O with/O his/O own/O children/O's/O governess/O?/O''/O

``/OBut/O what/O could/O I/O do/O?/O what/O could/O I/O do/O?/O''/O he/O kept/O saying/O in/O a/O pitiful/O
voice/O,/O not/O knowing/O what/O he/O was/O saying/O,/O as/O his/O head/O sank/O lower/O and/O lower/O./O

``/OYou/O are/O loathsome/O to/O me/O,/O repulsive/O!/O''/O she/O shrieked/O,/O getting/O more/O and/O
more/O heated/O./O ``/OYour/O tears/O mean/O nothing/O!/O You/O have/O never/O loved/O me/O;/O you/O have/O
neither/O heart/O nor/O honorable/O feeling/O!/O You/O are/O hateful/O to/O me/O,/O disgusting/O,/O
a/O stranger/O--/Oyes/O,/O a/O complete/O stranger/O!/O''/O With/O pain/O and/O wrath/O she/O uttered/O
the/O word/O so/O terrible/O to/O herself/O--/O_/Ostranger/O_/O./O

He/O looked/O at/O her/O,/O and/O the/O fury/O expressed/O in/O her/O face/O alarmed/O and/O amazed/O
him/O./O He/O did/O not/O understand/O how/O his/O pity/O for/O her/O exasperated/O her/O./O She/O saw/O
in/O him/O sympathy/O for/O her/O,/O but/O not/O love/O./O ``/ONo/O,/O she/O hates/O me/O./O She/O will/O not/O
forgive/O me/O,/O''/O he/O thought/O./O

``/OIt/O is/O awful/O!/O awful/O!/O''/O he/O said/O./O

At/O that/O moment/O in/O the/O next/O room/O a/O child/O began/O to/O cry/O;/O probably/O it/O had/O
fallen/O down/O./O Darya/PERSON Alexandrovna/PERSON listened/O,/O and/O her/O face/O suddenly/O
softened/O./O

She/O seemed/O to/O be/O pulling/O herself/O together/O for/O a/O few/O seconds/O,/O as/O though/O
she/O did/O not/O know/O where/O she/O was/O,/O and/O what/O she/O was/O doing/O,/O and/O getting/O up/O
rapidly/O,/O she/O moved/O towards/O the/O door/O./O

``/OWell/O,/O she/O loves/O my/O child/O,/O''/O he/O thought/O,/O noticing/O the/O change/O of/O her/O face/O
at/O the/O child/O's/O cry/O,/O ``/Omy/O child/O:/O how/O can/O she/O hate/O me/O?/O''/O

``/ODolly/O,/O one/O word/O more/O,/O''/O he/O said/O,/O following/O her/O./O

``/OIf/O you/O come/O near/O me/O,/O I/O will/O call/O in/O the/O servants/O,/O the/O children/O!/O They/O
may/O all/O know/O you/O are/O a/O scoundrel/O!/O I/O am/O going/O away/O at/O once/O,/O and/O you/O may/O
live/O here/O with/O your/O mistress/O!/O''/O

And/O she/O went/O out/O,/O slamming/O the/O door/O./O

Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON sighed/O,/O wiped/O his/O face/O,/O and/O with/O a/O subdued/O tread/O
walked/O out/O of/O the/O room/O./O ``/OMatvey/PERSON says/O she/O will/O come/O round/O;/O but/O how/O?/O I/O
do/On't/O see/O the/O least/O chance/O of/O it/O./O Ah/O,/O oh/O,/O how/O horrible/O it/O is/O!/O And/O how/O
vulgarly/O she/O shouted/O,/O''/O he/O said/O to/O himself/O,/O remembering/O her/O shriek/O and/O
the/O words/O--/O``/Oscoundrel/O''/O and/O ``/Omistress/O./O''/O ``/OAnd/O very/O likely/O the/O maids/O were/O
listening/O!/O Horribly/O vulgar/O!/O horrible/O!/O''/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON stood/O a/O few/O
seconds/O alone/O,/O wiped/O his/O face/O,/O squared/O his/O chest/O,/O and/O walked/O out/O of/O the/O
room/O./O

It/O was/O Friday/O,/O and/O in/O the/O dining/O room/O the/O German/O watchmaker/O was/O winding/O
up/O the/O clock/O./O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON remembered/O his/O joke/O about/O this/O
punctual/O,/O bald/O watchmaker/O,/O ``/Othat/O the/O German/O was/O wound/O up/O for/O a/O whole/O
lifetime/O himself/O,/O to/O wind/O up/O watches/O,/O''/O and/O he/O smiled/O./O Stepan/PERSON
Arkadyevitch/PERSON was/O fond/O of/O a/O joke/O:/O ``/OAnd/O maybe/O she/O will/O come/O round/O!/O That/O's/O
a/O good/O expression/O,/O `/O_/Ocome/O round/O,/O_/O'/O''/O he/O thought/O./O ``/OI/O must/O repeat/O that/O./O''/O

``/OMatvey/O!/O''/O he/O shouted/O./O ``/OArrange/O everything/O with/O Darya/PERSON in/O the/O sitting/O room/O
for/O Anna/PERSON Arkadyevna/PERSON,/O''/O he/O said/O to/O Matvey/PERSON when/O he/O came/O in/O./O

``/OYes/O,/O sir/O./O''/O

Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON put/O on/O his/O fur/O coat/O and/O went/O out/O onto/O the/O steps/O./O

``/OYou/O wo/On't/O dine/O at/O home/O?/O''/O said/O Matvey/PERSON,/O seeing/O him/O off/O./O

``/OThat/O's/O as/O it/O happens/O./O But/O here/O's/O for/O the/O housekeeping/O,/O''/O he/O said/O,/O taking/O
ten/O roubles/O from/O his/O pocketbook/O./O ``/OThat/O'll/O be/O enough/O./O''/O

``/OEnough/O or/O not/O enough/O,/O we/O must/O make/O it/O do/O,/O''/O said/O Matvey/PERSON,/O slamming/O the/O
carriage/O door/O and/O stepping/O back/O onto/O the/O steps/O./O

Darya/PERSON Alexandrovna/PERSON meanwhile/O having/O pacified/O the/O child/O,/O and/O knowing/O from/O
the/O sound/O of/O the/O carriage/O that/O he/O had/O gone/O off/O,/O went/O back/O again/O to/O her/O
bedroom/O./O It/O was/O her/O solitary/O refuge/O from/O the/O household/O cares/O which/O
crowded/O upon/O her/O directly/O she/O went/O out/O from/O it/O./O Even/O now/O,/O in/O the/O short/O
time/O she/O had/O been/O in/O the/O nursery/O,/O the/O English/O governess/O and/O Matrona/PERSON
Philimonovna/PERSON had/O succeeded/O in/O putting/O several/O questions/O to/O her/O,/O which/O
did/O not/O admit/O of/O delay/O,/O and/O which/O only/O she/O could/O answer/O:/O ``/OWhat/O were/O the/O
children/O to/O put/O on/O for/O their/O walk/O?/O Should/O they/O have/O any/O milk/O?/O Should/O not/O
a/O new/O cook/O be/O sent/O for/O?/O''/O

``/OAh/O,/O let/O me/O alone/O,/O let/O me/O alone/O!/O''/O she/O said/O,/O and/O going/O back/O to/O her/O
bedroom/O she/O sat/O down/O in/O the/O same/O place/O as/O she/O had/O sat/O when/O talking/O to/O
her/O husband/O,/O clasping/O tightly/O her/O thin/O hands/O with/O the/O rings/O that/O slipped/O
down/O on/O her/O bony/O fingers/O,/O and/O fell/O to/O going/O over/O in/O her/O memory/O all/O the/O
conversation/O./O ``/OHe/O has/O gone/O!/O But/O has/O he/O broken/O it/O off/O with/O her/O?/O''/O she/O
thought/O./O ``/OCan/O it/O be/O he/O sees/O her/O?/O Why/O did/On't/O I/O ask/O him/O!/O No/O,/O no/O,/O
reconciliation/O is/O impossible/O./O Even/O if/O we/O remain/O in/O the/O same/O house/O,/O we/O
are/O strangers/O--/Ostrangers/O forever/O!/O''/O She/O repeated/O again/O with/O special/O
significance/O the/O word/O so/O dreadful/O to/O her/O./O ``/OAnd/O how/O I/O loved/O him/O!/O my/O God/O,/O
how/O I/O loved/O him/O!/O.../O./O How/O I/O loved/O him/O!/O And/O now/O do/On't/O I/O love/O him/O?/O Do/On't/O I/O
love/O him/O more/O than/O before/O?/O The/O most/O horrible/O thing/O is/O,/O''/O she/O began/O,/O but/O
did/O not/O finish/O her/O thought/O,/O because/O Matrona/PERSON Philimonovna/PERSON put/O her/O head/O in/O
at/O the/O door/O./O

``/OLet/O us/O send/O for/O my/O brother/O,/O''/O she/O said/O;/O ``/Ohe/O can/O get/O a/O dinner/O anyway/O,/O or/O
we/O shall/O have/O the/O children/O getting/O nothing/O to/O eat/O till/O six/O again/O,/O like/O
yesterday/O./O''/O

``/OVery/O well/O,/O I/O will/O come/O directly/O and/O see/O about/O it/O./O But/O did/O you/O send/O for/O
some/O new/O milk/O?/O''/O

And/O Darya/PERSON Alexandrovna/PERSON plunged/O into/O the/O duties/O of/O the/O day/O,/O and/O drowned/O
her/O grief/O in/O them/O for/O a/O time/O./O



Chapter/O 5/O


Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON had/O learned/O easily/O at/O school/O,/O thanks/O to/O his/O
excellent/O abilities/O,/O but/O he/O had/O been/O idle/O and/O mischievous/O,/O and/O therefore/O
was/O one/O of/O the/O lowest/O in/O his/O class/O./O But/O in/O spite/O of/O his/O habitually/O
dissipated/O mode/O of/O life/O,/O his/O inferior/O grade/O in/O the/O service/O,/O and/O his/O
comparative/O youth/O,/O he/O occupied/O the/O honorable/O and/O lucrative/O position/O of/O
president/O of/O one/O of/O the/O government/O boards/O at/O Moscow/LOCATION./O This/O post/O he/O had/O
received/O through/O his/O sister/O Anna/PERSON's/O husband/O,/O Alexey/PERSON Alexandrovitch/PERSON
Karenin/PERSON,/O who/O held/O one/O of/O the/O most/O important/O positions/O in/O the/O ministry/O to/O
whose/O department/O the/O Moscow/LOCATION office/O belonged/O./O But/O if/O Karenin/PERSON had/O not/O got/O
his/O brother-in-law/O this/O berth/O,/O then/O through/O a/O hundred/O other/O
personages/O--/Obrothers/O,/O sisters/O,/O cousins/O,/O uncles/O,/O and/O aunts/O--/OStiva/PERSON Oblonsky/PERSON
would/O have/O received/O this/O post/O,/O or/O some/O other/O similar/O one/O,/O together/O with/O
the/O salary/O of/O six/O thousand/O absolutely/O needful/O for/O him/O,/O as/O his/O affairs/O,/O
in/O spite/O of/O his/O wife/O's/O considerable/O property/O,/O were/O in/O an/O embarrassed/O
condition/O./O

Half/O Moscow/LOCATION and/O Petersburg/PERSON were/O friends/O and/O relations/O of/O Stepan/PERSON
Arkadyevitch/PERSON./O He/O was/O born/O in/O the/O midst/O of/O those/O who/O had/O been/O and/O are/O the/O
powerful/O ones/O of/O this/O world/O./O One-third/O of/O the/O men/O in/O the/O government/O,/O the/O
older/O men/O,/O had/O been/O friends/O of/O his/O father/O's/O,/O and/O had/O known/O him/O in/O
petticoats/O;/O another/O third/O were/O his/O intimate/O chums/O,/O and/O the/O remainder/O
were/O friendly/O acquaintances/O./O Consequently/O the/O distributors/O of/O earthly/O
blessings/O in/O the/O shape/O of/O places/O,/O rents/O,/O shares/O,/O and/O such/O,/O were/O all/O his/O
friends/O,/O and/O could/O not/O overlook/O one/O of/O their/O own/O set/O;/O and/O Oblonsky/PERSON had/O
no/O need/O to/O make/O any/O special/O exertion/O to/O get/O a/O lucrative/O post/O./O He/O had/O
only/O not/O to/O refuse/O things/O,/O not/O to/O show/O jealousy/O,/O not/O to/O be/O quarrelsome/O
or/O take/O offense/O,/O all/O of/O which/O from/O his/O characteristic/O good/O nature/O he/O
never/O did/O./O It/O would/O have/O struck/O him/O as/O absurd/O if/O he/O had/O been/O told/O that/O
he/O would/O not/O get/O a/O position/O with/O the/O salary/O he/O required/O,/O especially/O as/O
he/O expected/O nothing/O out/O of/O the/O way/O;/O he/O only/O wanted/O what/O the/O men/O of/O his/O
own/O age/O and/O standing/O did/O get/O,/O and/O he/O was/O no/O worse/O qualified/O for/O
performing/O duties/O of/O the/O kind/O than/O any/O other/O man/O./O

Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON was/O not/O merely/O liked/O by/O all/O who/O knew/O him/O for/O his/O
good/O humor/O,/O but/O for/O his/O bright/O disposition/O,/O and/O his/O unquestionable/O
honesty/O./O In/O him/O,/O in/O his/O handsome/O,/O radiant/O figure/O,/O his/O sparkling/O eyes/O,/O
black/O hair/O and/O eyebrows/O,/O and/O the/O white/O and/O red/O of/O his/O face/O,/O there/O was/O
something/O which/O produced/O a/O physical/O effect/O of/O kindliness/O and/O good/O humor/O
on/O the/O people/O who/O met/O him/O./O ``/OAha/O!/O Stiva/O!/O Oblonsky/O!/O Here/O he/O is/O!/O''/O was/O
almost/O always/O said/O with/O a/O smile/O of/O delight/O on/O meeting/O him/O./O Even/O though/O
it/O happened/O at/O times/O that/O after/O a/O conversation/O with/O him/O it/O seemed/O that/O
nothing/O particularly/O delightful/O had/O happened/O,/O the/O next/O day/O,/O and/O the/O
next/O,/O every/O one/O was/O just/O as/O delighted/O at/O meeting/O him/O again/O./O

After/O filling/O for/O three/O years/O the/O post/O of/O president/O of/O one/O of/O the/O
government/O boards/O at/O Moscow/LOCATION,/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON had/O won/O the/O respect/O,/O as/O
well/O as/O the/O liking/O,/O of/O his/O fellow-officials/O,/O subordinates/O,/O and/O
superiors/O,/O and/O all/O who/O had/O had/O business/O with/O him/O./O The/O principal/O
qualities/O in/O Stepan/O Arkadyevitch/O which/O had/O gained/O him/O this/O universal/O
respect/O in/O the/O service/O consisted/O,/O in/O the/O first/O place/O,/O of/O his/O extreme/O
indulgence/O for/O others/O,/O founded/O on/O a/O consciousness/O of/O his/O own/O
shortcomings/O;/O secondly/O,/O of/O his/O perfect/O liberalism/O--/Onot/O the/O liberalism/O he/O
read/O of/O in/O the/O papers/O,/O but/O the/O liberalism/O that/O was/O in/O his/O blood/O,/O in/O
virtue/O of/O which/O he/O treated/O all/O men/O perfectly/O equally/O and/O exactly/O the/O
same/O,/O whatever/O their/O fortune/O or/O calling/O might/O be/O;/O and/O thirdly/O--/Othe/O most/O
important/O point/O--/Ohis/O complete/O indifference/O to/O the/O business/O in/O which/O he/O
was/O engaged/O,/O in/O consequence/O of/O which/O he/O was/O never/O carried/O away/O,/O and/O
never/O made/O mistakes/O./O

On/O reaching/O the/O offices/O of/O the/O board/O,/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON,/O escorted/O by/O a/O
deferential/O porter/O with/O a/O portfolio/O,/O went/O into/O his/O little/O private/O room/O,/O
put/O on/O his/O uniform/O,/O and/O went/O into/O the/O boardroom/O./O The/O clerks/O and/O copyists/O
all/O rose/O,/O greeting/O him/O with/O good-humored/O deference/O./O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON
moved/O quickly/O,/O as/O ever/O,/O to/O his/O place/O,/O shook/O hands/O with/O his/O colleagues/O,/O
and/O sat/O down/O./O He/O made/O a/O joke/O or/O two/O,/O and/O talked/O just/O as/O much/O as/O was/O
consistent/O with/O due/O decorum/O,/O and/O began/O work/O./O No/O one/O knew/O better/O than/O
Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON how/O to/O hit/O on/O the/O exact/O line/O between/O freedom/O,/O
simplicity/O,/O and/O official/O stiffness/O necessary/O for/O the/O agreeable/O conduct/O
of/O business/O./O A/O secretary/O,/O with/O the/O good-humored/O deference/O common/O to/O
every/O one/O in/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON's/O office/O,/O came/O up/O with/O papers/O,/O and/O
began/O to/O speak/O in/O the/O familiar/O and/O easy/O tone/O which/O had/O been/O introduced/O
by/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON./O

``/OWe/O have/O succeeded/O in/O getting/O the/O information/O from/O the/O government/O
department/O of/O Penza/PERSON./O Here/O,/O would/O you/O care/O?/O.../O''/O

``/OYou/O've/O got/O them/O at/O last/O?/O''/O said/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON,/O laying/O his/O finger/O
on/O the/O paper/O./O ``/ONow/O,/O gentlemen/O.../O''/O

And/O the/O sitting/O of/O the/O board/O began/O./O

``/OIf/O they/O knew/O,/O''/O he/O thought/O,/O bending/O his/O head/O with/O a/O significant/O air/O as/O
he/O listened/O to/O the/O report/O,/O ``/Owhat/O a/O guilty/O little/O boy/O their/O president/O was/O
half/O an/O hour/O ago/O./O''/O And/O his/O eyes/O were/O laughing/O during/O the/O reading/O of/O the/O
report/O./O Till/O two/O o'clock/O the/O sitting/O would/O go/O on/O without/O a/O break/O,/O and/O at/O
two/O o'clock/O there/O would/O be/O an/O interval/O and/O luncheon/O./O

It/O was/O not/O yet/O two/O,/O when/O the/O large/O glass/O doors/O of/O the/O boardroom/O suddenly/O
opened/O and/O someone/O came/O in/O./O

All/O the/O officials/O sitting/O on/O the/O further/O side/O under/O the/O portrait/O of/O the/O
Tsar/O and/O the/O eagle/O,/O delighted/O at/O any/O distraction/O,/O looked/O round/O at/O the/O
door/O;/O but/O the/O doorkeeper/O standing/O at/O the/O door/O at/O once/O drove/O out/O the/O
intruder/O,/O and/O closed/O the/O glass/O door/O after/O him/O./O

When/O the/O case/O had/O been/O read/O through/O,/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON got/O up/O and/O
stretched/O,/O and/O by/O way/O of/O tribute/O to/O the/O liberalism/O of/O the/O times/O took/O out/O
a/O cigarette/O in/O the/O boardroom/O and/O went/O into/O his/O private/O room/O./O Two/O of/O the/O
members/O of/O the/O board/O,/O the/O old/O veteran/O in/O the/O service/O,/O Nikitin/ORGANIZATION,/O and/O the/O
_/OKammerjunker/PERSON Grinevitch/PERSON_/O,/O went/O in/O with/O him/O./O

``/OWe/O shall/O have/O time/O to/O finish/O after/O lunch/O,/O''/O said/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON./O

``/OTo/O be/O sure/O we/O shall/O!/O''/O said/O Nikitin/PERSON./O

``/OA/O pretty/O sharp/O fellow/O this/O Fomin/PERSON must/O be/O,/O''/O said/O Grinevitch/PERSON of/O one/O of/O
the/O persons/O taking/O part/O in/O the/O case/O they/O were/O examining/O./O

Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON frowned/O at/O Grinevitch/PERSON's/O words/O,/O giving/O him/O thereby/O to/O
understand/O that/O it/O was/O improper/O to/O pass/O judgment/O prematurely/O,/O and/O made/O
him/O no/O reply/O./O

``/OWho/O was/O that/O came/O in/O?/O''/O he/O asked/O the/O doorkeeper/O./O

``/OSomeone/O,/O your/O excellency/O,/O crept/O in/O without/O permission/O directly/O my/O back/O
was/O turned/O./O He/O was/O asking/O for/O you/O./O I/O told/O him/O:/O when/O the/O members/O come/O
out/O,/O then/O.../O''/O

``/OWhere/O is/O he/O?/O''/O

``/OMaybe/O he/O's/O gone/O into/O the/O passage/O,/O but/O here/O he/O comes/O anyway/O./O That/O is/O
he/O,/O''/O said/O the/O doorkeeper/O,/O pointing/O to/O a/O strongly/O built/O,/O broad-shouldered/O
man/O with/O a/O curly/O beard/O,/O who/O,/O without/O taking/O off/O his/O sheepskin/O cap/O,/O was/O
running/O lightly/O and/O rapidly/O up/O the/O worn/O steps/O of/O the/O stone/O staircase/O./O
One/O of/O the/O members/O going/O down/O--/Oa/O lean/O official/O with/O a/O portfolio/O--/Ostood/O out/O
of/O his/O way/O and/O looked/O disapprovingly/O at/O the/O legs/O of/O the/O stranger/O,/O then/O
glanced/O inquiringly/O at/O Oblonsky/LOCATION./O

Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON was/O standing/O at/O the/O top/O of/O the/O stairs/O./O His/O
good-naturedly/O beaming/O face/O above/O the/O embroidered/O collar/O of/O his/O uniform/O
beamed/O more/O than/O ever/O when/O he/O recognized/O the/O man/O coming/O up/O./O

``/OWhy/O,/O it/O's/O actually/O you/O,/O Levin/PERSON,/O at/O last/O!/O''/O he/O said/O with/O a/O friendly/O
mocking/O smile/O,/O scanning/O Levin/PERSON as/O he/O approached/O./O ``/OHow/O is/O it/O you/O have/O
deigned/O to/O look/O me/O up/O in/O this/O den/O?/O''/O said/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON,/O and/O not/O
content/O with/O shaking/O hands/O,/O he/O kissed/O his/O friend/O./O ``/OHave/O you/O been/O here/O
long/O?/O''/O

``/OI/O have/O just/O come/O,/O and/O very/O much/O wanted/O to/O see/O you/O,/O''/O said/O Levin/PERSON,/O looking/O
shyly/O and/O at/O the/O same/O time/O angrily/O and/O uneasily/O around/O./O

``/OWell/O,/O let/O's/O go/O into/O my/O room/O,/O''/O said/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON,/O who/O knew/O his/O
friend/O's/O sensitive/O and/O irritable/O shyness/O,/O and/O,/O taking/O his/O arm/O,/O he/O drew/O
him/O along/O,/O as/O though/O guiding/O him/O through/O dangers/O./O

Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON was/O on/O familiar/O terms/O with/O almost/O all/O his/O
acquaintances/O,/O and/O called/O almost/O all/O of/O them/O by/O their/O Christian/O names/O:/O
old/O men/O of/O sixty/O,/O boys/O of/O twenty/O,/O actors/O,/O ministers/O,/O merchants/O,/O and/O
adjutant-generals/O,/O so/O that/O many/O of/O his/O intimate/O chums/O were/O to/O be/O found/O
at/O the/O extreme/O ends/O of/O the/O social/O ladder/O,/O and/O would/O have/O been/O very/O much/O
surprised/O to/O learn/O that/O they/O had/O,/O through/O the/O medium/O of/O Oblonsky/LOCATION,/O
something/O in/O common/O./O He/O was/O the/O familiar/O friend/O of/O everyone/O with/O whom/O he/O
took/O a/O glass/O of/O champagne/O,/O and/O he/O took/O a/O glass/O of/O champagne/O with/O
everyone/O,/O and/O when/O in/O consequence/O he/O met/O any/O of/O his/O disreputable/O chums/O,/O
as/O he/O used/O in/O joke/O to/O call/O many/O of/O his/O friends/O,/O in/O the/O presence/O of/O his/O
subordinates/O,/O he/O well/O knew/O how/O,/O with/O his/O characteristic/O tact/O,/O to/O
diminish/O the/O disagreeable/O impression/O made/O on/O them/O./O Levin/PERSON was/O not/O a/O
disreputable/O chum/O,/O but/O Oblonsky/PERSON,/O with/O his/O ready/O tact/O,/O felt/O that/O Levin/PERSON
fancied/O he/O might/O not/O care/O to/O show/O his/O intimacy/O with/O him/O before/O his/O
subordinates/O,/O and/O so/O he/O made/O haste/O to/O take/O him/O off/O into/O his/O room/O./O

Levin/PERSON was/O almost/O of/O the/O same/O age/O as/O Oblonsky/PERSON;/O their/O intimacy/O did/O not/O
rest/O merely/O on/O champagne/O./O Levin/PERSON had/O been/O the/O friend/O and/O companion/O of/O his/O
early/O youth/O./O They/O were/O fond/O of/O one/O another/O in/O spite/O of/O the/O difference/O of/O
their/O characters/O and/O tastes/O,/O as/O friends/O are/O fond/O of/O one/O another/O who/O have/O
been/O together/O in/O early/O youth/O./O But/O in/O spite/O of/O this/O,/O each/O of/O them/O--/Oas/O is/O
often/O the/O way/O with/O men/O who/O have/O selected/O careers/O of/O different/O
kinds/O--/Othough/O in/O discussion/O he/O would/O even/O justify/O the/O other/O's/O career/O,/O in/O
his/O heart/O despised/O it/O./O It/O seemed/O to/O each/O of/O them/O that/O the/O life/O he/O led/O
himself/O was/O the/O only/O real/O life/O,/O and/O the/O life/O led/O by/O his/O friend/O was/O a/O
mere/O phantasm/O./O Oblonsky/PERSON could/O not/O restrain/O a/O slight/O mocking/O smile/O at/O the/O
sight/O of/O Levin/PERSON./O How/O often/O he/O had/O seen/O him/O come/O up/O to/O Moscow/LOCATION from/O the/O
country/O where/O he/O was/O doing/O something/O,/O but/O what/O precisely/O Stepan/PERSON
Arkadyevitch/PERSON could/O never/O quite/O make/O out/O,/O and/O indeed/O he/O took/O no/O interest/O
in/O the/O matter/O./O Levin/PERSON arrived/O in/O Moscow/LOCATION always/O excited/O and/O in/O a/O hurry/O,/O
rather/O ill/O at/O ease/O and/O irritated/O by/O his/O own/O want/O of/O ease/O,/O and/O for/O the/O
most/O part/O with/O a/O perfectly/O new/O,/O unexpected/O view/O of/O things/O./O Stepan/PERSON
Arkadyevitch/PERSON laughed/O at/O this/O,/O and/O liked/O it/O./O In/O the/O same/O way/O Levin/PERSON in/O his/O
heart/O despised/O the/O town/O mode/O of/O life/O of/O his/O friend/O,/O and/O his/O official/O
duties/O,/O which/O he/O laughed/O at/O,/O and/O regarded/O as/O trifling/O./O But/O the/O
difference/O was/O that/O Oblonsky/PERSON,/O as/O he/O was/O doing/O the/O same/O as/O every/O one/O did/O,/O
laughed/O complacently/O and/O good-humoredly/O,/O while/O Levin/PERSON laughed/O without/O
complacency/O and/O sometimes/O angrily/O./O

``/OWe/O have/O long/O been/O expecting/O you/O,/O''/O said/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON,/O going/O into/O
his/O room/O and/O letting/O Levin/PERSON's/O hand/O go/O as/O though/O to/O show/O that/O here/O all/O
danger/O was/O over/O./O ``/OI/O am/O very/O,/O very/O glad/O to/O see/O you/O,/O''/O he/O went/O on/O./O ``/OWell/O,/O
how/O are/O you/O?/O Eh/O?/O When/O did/O you/O come/O?/O''/O

Levin/PERSON was/O silent/O,/O looking/O at/O the/O unknown/O faces/O of/O Oblonsky/PERSON's/O two/O
companions/O,/O and/O especially/O at/O the/O hand/O of/O the/O elegant/O Grinevitch/O,/O which/O
had/O such/O long/O white/O fingers/O,/O such/O long/O yellow/O filbert-shaped/O nails/O,/O and/O
such/O huge/O shining/O studs/O on/O the/O shirt-cuff/O,/O that/O apparently/O they/O absorbed/O
all/O his/O attention/O,/O and/O allowed/O him/O no/O freedom/O of/O thought/O./O Oblonsky/PERSON
noticed/O this/O at/O once/O,/O and/O smiled/O./O

``/OAh/O,/O to/O be/O sure/O,/O let/O me/O introduce/O you/O,/O''/O he/O said/O./O ``/OMy/O colleagues/O:/O Philip/PERSON
Ivanitch/PERSON Nikitin/PERSON,/O Mihail/PERSON Stanislavitch/PERSON Grinevitch/PERSON''/O--/Oand/O turning/O to/O
Levin/PERSON--/O``/Oa/O district/O councilor/O,/O a/O modern/O district/O councilman/O,/O a/O gymnast/O who/O
lifts/O thirteen/O stone/O with/O one/O hand/O,/O a/O cattle-breeder/O and/O sportsman/O,/O and/O
my/O friend/O,/O Konstantin/PERSON Dmitrievitch/PERSON Levin/PERSON,/O the/O brother/O of/O Sergey/PERSON
Ivanovitch/PERSON Koznishev/PERSON./O''/O

``/ODelighted/O,/O''/O said/O the/O veteran/O./O

``/OI/O have/O the/O honor/O of/O knowing/O your/O brother/O,/O Sergey/PERSON Ivanovitch/PERSON,/O''/O said/O
Grinevitch/PERSON,/O holding/O out/O his/O slender/O hand/O with/O its/O long/O nails/O./O

Levin/PERSON frowned/O,/O shook/O hands/O coldly/O,/O and/O at/O once/O turned/O to/O Oblonsky/LOCATION./O
Though/O he/O had/O a/O great/O respect/O for/O his/O half-brother/O,/O an/O author/O well/O known/O
to/O all/O Russia/LOCATION,/O he/O could/O not/O endure/O it/O when/O people/O treated/O him/O not/O as/O
Konstantin/PERSON Levin/PERSON,/O but/O as/O the/O brother/O of/O the/O celebrated/O Koznishev/PERSON./O

``/ONo/O,/O I/O am/O no/O longer/O a/O district/O councilor/O./O I/O have/O quarreled/O with/O them/O
all/O,/O and/O do/On't/O go/O to/O the/O meetings/O any/O more/O,/O''/O he/O said/O,/O turning/O to/O
Oblonsky/PERSON./O

``/OYou/O've/O been/O quick/O about/O it/O!/O''/O said/O Oblonsky/PERSON with/O a/O smile/O./O ``/OBut/O how/O?/O
why/O?/O''/O

``/OIt/O's/O a/O long/O story/O./O I/O will/O tell/O you/O some/O time/O,/O''/O said/O Levin/PERSON,/O but/O he/O began/O
telling/O him/O at/O once/O./O ``/OWell/O,/O to/O put/O it/O shortly/O,/O I/O was/O convinced/O that/O
nothing/O was/O really/O done/O by/O the/O district/O councils/O,/O or/O ever/O could/O be/O,/O''/O he/O
began/O,/O as/O though/O some/O one/O had/O just/O insulted/O him/O./O ``/OOn/O one/O side/O it/O's/O a/O
plaything/O;/O they/O play/O at/O being/O a/O parliament/O,/O and/O I/O'm/O neither/O young/O enough/O
nor/O old/O enough/O to/O find/O amusement/O in/O playthings/O;/O and/O on/O the/O other/O side/O''/O
-LRB-/Ohe/O stammered/O-RRB-/O ``/Oit/O's/O a/O means/O for/O the/O coterie/O of/O the/O district/O to/O make/O
money/O./O Formerly/O they/O had/O wardships/O,/O courts/O of/O justice/O,/O now/O they/O have/O the/O
district/O council/O--/Onot/O in/O the/O form/O of/O bribes/O,/O but/O in/O the/O form/O of/O unearned/O
salary/O,/O''/O he/O said/O,/O as/O hotly/O as/O though/O someone/O of/O those/O present/O had/O
opposed/O his/O opinion/O./O

``/OAha/O!/O You/O're/O in/O a/O new/O phase/O again/O,/O I/O see/O--/Oa/O conservative/O,/O''/O said/O Stepan/PERSON
Arkadyevitch/PERSON./O ``/OHowever/O,/O we/O can/O go/O into/O that/O later/O./O''/O

``/OYes/O,/O later/O./O But/O I/O wanted/O to/O see/O you/O,/O''/O said/O Levin/PERSON,/O looking/O with/O hatred/O
at/O Grinevitch/PERSON's/O hand/O./O

Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON gave/O a/O scarcely/O perceptible/O smile/O./O

``/OHow/O was/O it/O you/O used/O to/O say/O you/O would/O never/O wear/O European/O dress/O again/O?/O''/O
he/O said/O,/O scanning/O his/O new/O suit/O,/O obviously/O cut/O by/O a/O French/O tailor/O./O ``/OAh/O!/O I/O
see/O:/O a/O new/O phase/O./O''/O

Levin/PERSON suddenly/O blushed/O,/O not/O as/O grown/O men/O blush/O,/O slightly/O,/O without/O being/O
themselves/O aware/O of/O it/O,/O but/O as/O boys/O blush/O,/O feeling/O that/O they/O are/O
ridiculous/O through/O their/O shyness/O,/O and/O consequently/O ashamed/O of/O it/O and/O
blushing/O still/O more/O,/O almost/O to/O the/O point/O of/O tears/O./O And/O it/O was/O so/O strange/O
to/O see/O this/O sensible/O,/O manly/O face/O in/O such/O a/O childish/O plight/O,/O that/O
Oblonsky/PERSON left/O off/O looking/O at/O him/O./O

``/OOh/O,/O where/O shall/O we/O meet/O?/O You/O know/O I/O want/O very/O much/O to/O talk/O to/O you/O,/O''/O
said/O Levin/PERSON./O

Oblonsky/PERSON seemed/O to/O ponder/O./O

``/OI/O'll/O tell/O you/O what/O:/O let/O's/O go/O to/O Gurin/PERSON's/O to/O lunch/O,/O and/O there/O we/O can/O
talk/O./O I/O am/O free/O till/O three/O./O''/O

``/ONo/O,/O''/O answered/O Levin/PERSON,/O after/O an/O instant/O's/O thought/O,/O ``/OI/O have/O got/O to/O go/O on/O
somewhere/O else/O./O''/O

``/OAll/O right/O,/O then/O,/O let/O's/O dine/O together/O./O''/O

``/ODine/O together/O?/O But/O I/O have/O nothing/O very/O particular/O,/O only/O a/O few/O words/O to/O
say/O,/O and/O a/O question/O I/O want/O to/O ask/O you/O,/O and/O we/O can/O have/O a/O talk/O
afterwards/O./O''/O

``/OWell/O,/O say/O the/O few/O words/O,/O then/O,/O at/O once/O,/O and/O we/O'll/O gossip/O after/O dinner/O./O''/O

``/OWell/O,/O it/O's/O this/O,/O''/O said/O Levin/PERSON;/O ``/Obut/O it/O's/O of/O no/O importance/O,/O though/O./O''/O

His/O face/O all/O at/O once/O took/O an/O expression/O of/O anger/O from/O the/O effort/O he/O was/O
making/O to/O surmount/O his/O shyness/O./O

``/OWhat/O are/O the/O Shtcherbatskys/O doing/O?/O Everything/O as/O it/O used/O to/O be/O?/O''/O he/O
said/O./O

Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON,/O who/O had/O long/O known/O that/O Levin/PERSON was/O in/O love/O with/O his/O
sister-in-law/O,/O Kitty/PERSON,/O gave/O a/O hardly/O perceptible/O smile/O,/O and/O his/O eyes/O
sparkled/O merrily/O./O

``/OYou/O said/O a/O few/O words/O,/O but/O I/O ca/On't/O answer/O in/O a/O few/O words/O,/O because/O.../O./O
Excuse/O me/O a/O minute/O.../O''/O

A/O secretary/O came/O in/O,/O with/O respectful/O familiarity/O and/O the/O modest/O
consciousness/O,/O characteristic/O of/O every/O secretary/O,/O of/O superiority/O to/O his/O
chief/O in/O the/O knowledge/O of/O their/O business/O;/O he/O went/O up/O to/O Oblonsky/PERSON with/O
some/O papers/O,/O and/O began/O,/O under/O pretense/O of/O asking/O a/O question/O,/O to/O explain/O
some/O objection/O./O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON,/O without/O hearing/O him/O out/O,/O laid/O his/O
hand/O genially/O on/O the/O secretary/O's/O sleeve/O./O

``/ONo/O,/O you/O do/O as/O I/O told/O you/O,/O''/O he/O said/O,/O softening/O his/O words/O with/O a/O smile/O,/O
and/O with/O a/O brief/O explanation/O of/O his/O view/O of/O the/O matter/O he/O turned/O away/O
from/O the/O papers/O,/O and/O said/O:/O ``/OSo/O do/O it/O that/O way/O,/O if/O you/O please/O,/O Zahar/PERSON
Nikititch/PERSON./O''/O

The/O secretary/O retired/O in/O confusion/O./O During/O the/O consultation/O with/O the/O
secretary/O Levin/PERSON had/O completely/O recovered/O from/O his/O embarrassment/O./O He/O was/O
standing/O with/O his/O elbows/O on/O the/O back/O of/O a/O chair/O,/O and/O on/O his/O face/O was/O a/O
look/O of/O ironical/O attention/O./O

``/OI/O do/On't/O understand/O it/O,/O I/O do/On't/O understand/O it/O,/O''/O he/O said/O./O

``/OWhat/O do/On't/O you/O understand/O?/O''/O said/O Oblonsky/PERSON,/O smiling/O as/O brightly/O as/O ever/O,/O
and/O picking/O up/O a/O cigarette/O./O He/O expected/O some/O queer/O outburst/O from/O Levin/PERSON./O

``/OI/O do/On't/O understand/O what/O you/O are/O doing/O,/O''/O said/O Levin/PERSON,/O shrugging/O his/O
shoulders/O./O ``/OHow/O can/O you/O do/O it/O seriously/O?/O''/O

``/OWhy/O not/O?/O''/O

``/OWhy/O,/O because/O there/O's/O nothing/O in/O it/O./O''/O

``/OYou/O think/O so/O,/O but/O we/O're/O overwhelmed/O with/O work/O./O''/O

``/OOn/O paper/O./O But/O,/O there/O,/O you/O've/O a/O gift/O for/O it/O,/O''/O added/O Levin/PERSON./O

``/OThat/O's/O to/O say/O,/O you/O think/O there/O's/O a/O lack/O of/O something/O in/O me/O?/O''/O

``/OPerhaps/O so/O,/O''/O said/O Levin/PERSON./O ``/OBut/O all/O the/O same/O I/O admire/O your/O grandeur/O,/O and/O
am/O proud/O that/O I/O've/O a/O friend/O in/O such/O a/O great/O person/O./O You/O've/O not/O answered/O
my/O question/O,/O though/O,/O''/O he/O went/O on/O,/O with/O a/O desperate/O effort/O looking/O
Oblonsky/PERSON straight/O in/O the/O face/O./O

``/OOh/O,/O that/O's/O all/O very/O well/O./O You/O wait/O a/O bit/O,/O and/O you/O'll/O come/O to/O this/O
yourself/O./O It/O's/O very/O nice/O for/O you/O to/O have/O over/O six/O thousand/O acres/O in/O the/O
Karazinsky/LOCATION district/O,/O and/O such/O muscles/O,/O and/O the/O freshness/O of/O a/O girl/O of/O
twelve/O;/O still/O you/O'll/O be/O one/O of/O us/O one/O day/O./O Yes/O,/O as/O to/O your/O question/O,/O
there/O is/O no/O change/O,/O but/O it/O's/O a/O pity/O you/O've/O been/O away/O so/O long/O./O''/O

``/OOh/O,/O why/O so/O?/O''/O Levin/PERSON queried/O,/O panic-stricken/O./O

``/OOh/O,/O nothing/O,/O''/O responded/O Oblonsky/PERSON./O ``/OWe/O'll/O talk/O it/O over/O./O But/O what/O's/O
brought/O you/O up/O to/O town/O?/O''/O

``/OOh/O,/O we/O'll/O talk/O about/O that/O,/O too/O,/O later/O on/O,/O''/O said/O Levin/PERSON,/O reddening/O again/O
up/O to/O his/O ears/O./O

``/OAll/O right/O./O I/O see/O,/O''/O said/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON./O ``/OI/O should/O ask/O you/O to/O come/O
to/O us/O,/O you/O know/O,/O but/O my/O wife/O's/O not/O quite/O the/O thing/O./O But/O I/O tell/O you/O what/O;/O
if/O you/O want/O to/O see/O them/O,/O they/O're/O sure/O now/O to/O be/O at/O the/O Zoological/LOCATION
Gardens/LOCATION from/O four/O to/O five/O./O Kitty/PERSON skates/O./O You/O drive/O along/O there/O,/O and/O I/O'll/O
come/O and/O fetch/O you/O,/O and/O we/O'll/O go/O and/O dine/O somewhere/O together/O./O''/O

``/OCapital/O./O So/O good-bye/O till/O then/O./O''/O

``/ONow/O mind/O,/O you/O'll/O forget/O,/O I/O know/O you/O,/O or/O rush/O off/O home/O to/O the/O country/O!/O''/O
Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON called/O out/O laughing/O./O

``/ONo/O,/O truly/O!/O''/O

And/O Levin/PERSON went/O out/O of/O the/O room/O,/O only/O when/O he/O was/O in/O the/O doorway/O
remembering/O that/O he/O had/O forgotten/O to/O take/O leave/O of/O Oblonsky/PERSON's/O
colleagues/O./O

``/OThat/O gentleman/O must/O be/O a/O man/O of/O great/O energy/O,/O''/O said/O Grinevitch/PERSON,/O when/O
Levin/PERSON had/O gone/O away/O./O

``/OYes/O,/O my/O dear/O boy/O,/O''/O said/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON,/O nodding/O his/O head/O,/O ``/Ohe/O's/O a/O
lucky/O fellow/O!/O Over/O six/O thousand/O acres/O in/O the/O Karazinsky/LOCATION district/O;/O
everything/O before/O him/O;/O and/O what/O youth/O and/O vigor/O!/O Not/O like/O some/O of/O us/O./O''/O

``/OYou/O have/O a/O great/O deal/O to/O complain/O of/O,/O have/On't/O you/O,/O Stepan/PERSON
Arkadyevitch/PERSON?/O''/O

``/OAh/O,/O yes/O,/O I/O'm/O in/O a/O poor/O way/O,/O a/O bad/O way/O,/O''/O said/O Stepan/PERSON Arkadyevitch/PERSON with/O a/O
heavy/O sigh/O./O



Chapter/O 6/O


When/O Oblonsky/PERSON asked/O Levin/PERSON what/O had/O brought/O him/O to/O town/O,/O Levin/PERSON blushed/O,/O
and/O was/O furious/O with/O himself/O for/O blushing/O,/O because/O he/O could/O not/O answer/O,/O
``/OI/O have/O come/O to/O make/O your/O sister-in-law/O an/O offer/O,/O''/O though/O that/O was/O
precisely/O what/O he/O had/O come/O for/O./O

The/O families/O of/O the/O Levins/PERSON and/O the/O Shtcherbatskys/O were/O old/O,/O noble/O Moscow/LOCATION
families/O,/O and/O had/O always/O been/O on/O intimate/O and/O friendly/O terms/O./O This/O
intimacy/O had/O grown/O still/O closer/O during/O Levin/PERSON's/O student/O days/O./O He/O had/O both/O
prepared/O for/O the/O university/O with/O the/O young/O Prince/PERSON Shtcherbatsky/PERSON,/O the/O
brother/O of/O Kitty/PERSON and/O Dolly/PERSON,/O and/O had/O entered/O at/O the/O same/O time/O with/O him/O./O
In/O those/O days/O Levin/PERSON used/O often/O to/O be/O in/O the/O Shtcherbatskys/O'/O house/O,/O and/O
he/O was/O in/O love/O with/O the/O Shtcherbatsky/O household/O./O Strange/O as/O it/O may/O
appear/O,/O it/O was/O with/O the/O household/O,/O the/O family/O,/O that/O Konstantin/PERSON Levin/PERSON was/O
in/O love/O,/O especially/O with/O the/O feminine/O half/O of/O the/O household/O./O Levin/PERSON did/O
not/O remember/O his/O own/O mother/O,/O and/O his/O only/O sister/O was/O older/O than/O he/O was/O,/O
so/O that/O it/O was/O in/O the/O Shtcherbatskys/O'/O house/O that/O he/O saw/O for/O the/O first/O
time/O that/O inner/O life/O of/O an/O old/O,/O noble/O,/O cultivated/O,/O and/O honorable/O family/O
of/O which/O he/O had/O been/O deprived/O by/O the/O death/O of/O his/O father/O and/O mother/O./O All/O
the/O members/O of/O that/O family/O,/O especially/O the/O feminine/O half/O,/O were/O pictured/O
by/O him/O,/O as/O it/O were/O,/O wrapped/O about/O with/O a/O mysterious/O poetical/O veil/O,/O and/O
he/O not/O only/O perceived/O no/O defects/O whatever/O in/O them/O,/O but/O under/O the/O
poetical/O veil/O that/O shrouded/O them/O he/O assumed/O the/O existence/O of/O the/O
loftiest/O sentiments/O and/O every/O possible/O perfection/O./O Why/O it/O was/O the/O three/O
young/O ladies/O had/O one/O day/O to/O speak/O French/O,/O and/O the/O next/O English/O;/O why/O it/O
was/O that/O at/O certain/O hours/O they/O played/O by/O turns/O on/O the/O piano/O,/O the/O sounds/O
of/O which/O were/O audible/O in/O their/O brother/O's/O room/O above/O,/O where/O the/O students/O
used/O to/O work/O;/O why/O they/O were/O visited/O by/O those/O professors/O of/O French/O
literature/O,/O of/O music/O,/O of/O drawing/O,/O of/O dancing/O;/O why/O at/O certain/O hours/O all/O
the/O three/O young/O ladies/O,/O with/O Mademoiselle/PERSON Linon/PERSON,/O drove/O in/O the/O coach/O to/O
the/O Tversky/PERSON boulevard/O,/O dressed/O in/O their/O satin/O cloaks/O,/O Dolly/PERSON in/O a/O long/O
one/O,/O Natalia/PERSON in/O a/O half-long/O one/O,/O and/O Kitty/PERSON in/O one/O so/O short/O that/O her/O
shapely/O legs/O in/O tightly-drawn/O red/O stockings/O were/O visible/O to/O all/O
beholders/O;/O why/O it/O was/O they/O had/O to/O walk/O about/O the/O Tversky/PERSON boulevard/O
escorted/O by/O a/O footman/O with/O a/O gold/O cockade/O in/O his/O hat/O--/Oall/O this/O and/O much/O
more/O that/O was/O done/O in/O their/O mysterious/O world/O he/O did/O not/O understand/O,/O but/O
he/O was/O sure/O that/O everything/O that/O was/O done/O there/O was/O very/O good/O,/O and/O he/O
was/O in/O love/O precisely/O with/O the/O mystery/O of/O the/O proceedings/O./O

In/O his/O student/O days/O he/O had/O all/O but/O been/O in/O love/O with/O the/O eldest/O,/O Dolly/PERSON,/O
but/O she/O was/O soon/O married/O to/O Oblonsky/PERSON./O Then/O he/O began/O being/O in/O love/O with/O
the/O second/O./O He/O felt/O,/O as/O it/O were/O,/O that/O he/O had/O to/O be/O in/O love/O with/O one/O of/O
the/O sisters/O,/O only/O he/O could/O not/O quite/O make/O out/O which/O./O But/O Natalia/PERSON,/O too/O,/O
had/O hardly/O made/O her/O appearance/O in/O the/O world/O when/O she/O married/O the/O
diplomat/O Lvov/PERSON./O Kitty/PERSON was/O still/O a/O child/O when/O Levin/PERSON left/O the/O university/O./O
Young/O Shtcherbatsky/PERSON went/O into/O the/O navy/O,/O was/O drowned/O in/O the/O Baltic/O,/O and/O
Levin/PERSON's/O relations/O with/O the/O Shtcherbatskys/O,/O in/O spite/O of/O his/O friendship/O
with/O Oblonsky/PERSON,/O became/O less/O intimate/O./O But/O when/O early/O in/O the/O winter/O of/O
this/O year/O Levin/PERSON came/O to/O Moscow/LOCATION,/O after/O a/O year/O in/O the/O country/O,/O and/O saw/O the/O
Shtcherbatskys/O,/O he/O realized/O which/O of/O the/O three/O sisters/O he/O was/O indeed/O
destined/O to/O love/O./O

One/O would/O have/O thought/O that/O nothing/O could/O be/O simpler/O than/O for/O him/O,/O a/O man/O
of/O good/O family/O,/O rather/O rich/O than/O poor/O,/O and/O thirty-two/O years/O old/O,/O to/O make/O
the/O young/O Princess/O Shtcherbatskaya/PERSON an/O offer/O of/O marriage/O;/O in/O all/O
likelihood/O he/O would/O at/O once/O have/O been/O looked/O upon/O as/O a/O good/O match/O./O But/O
Levin/PERSON was/O in/O love/O,/O and/O so/O it/O seemed/O to/O him/O that/O Kitty/PERSON was/O so/O perfect/O in/O
every/O respect/O that/O she/O was/O a/O creature/O far/O above/O everything/O earthly/O;/O and/O
that/O he/O was/O a/O creature/O so/O low/O and/O so/O earthly/O that/O it/O could/O not/O even/O be/O
conceived/O that/O other/O people/O and/O she/O herself/O could/O regard/O him/O as/O worthy/O
of/O her/O./O

After/O spending/O two/O months/O in/O Moscow/LOCATION in/O a/O state/O of/O enchantment/O,/O seeing/O
Kitty/PERSON almost/O every/O day/O in/O society/O,/O into/O which/O he/O went/O so/O as/O to/O meet/O her/O,/O
he/O abruptly/O decided/O that/O it/O could/O not/O be/O,/O and/O went/O back/O to/O the/O country/O./O

Levin/PERSON's/O conviction/O that/O it/O could/O not/O be/O was/O founded/O on/O the/O idea/O that/O in/O
the/O eyes/O of/O her/O family/O he/O was/O a/O disadvantageous/O and/O worthless/O match/O for/O
the/O charming/O Kitty/PERSON,/O and/O that/O Kitty/PERSON herself/O could/O not/O love/O him/O./O In/O her/O
family/O's/O eyes/O he/O had/O no/O ordinary/O,/O definite/O career/O and/O position/O in/O
society/O,/O while/O his/O contemporaries/O by/O this/O time/O,/O when/O he/O was/O thirty-two/O,/O
were/O already/O,/O one/O a/O colonel/O,/O and/O another/O a/O professor/O,/O another/O director/O
of/O a/O bank/O and/O railways/O,/O or/O president/O of/O a/O board/O like/O Oblonsky/PERSON./O But/O he/O
-LRB-/Ohe/O knew/O very/O well/O how/O he/O must/O appear/O to/O others/O-RRB-/O was/O a/O country/O
gentleman/O,/O occupied/O in/O breeding/O cattle/O,/O shooting/O game/O,/O and/O building/O
barns/O;/O in/O other/O words/O,/O a/O fellow/O of/O no/O ability/O,/O who/O had/O not/O turned/O out/O
well/O,/O and/O who/O was/O doing/O just/O what/O,/O according/O to/O the/O ideas/O of/O the/O world/O,/O
is/O done/O by/O people/O fit/O for/O nothing/O else/O./O

The/O mysterious/O,/O enchanting/O Kitty/PERSON herself/O could/O not/O love/O such/O an/O ugly/O
person/O as/O he/O conceived/O himself/O to/O be/O,/O and/O,/O above/O all/O,/O such/O an/O ordinary/O,/O
in/O no/O way/O striking/O person/O./O Moreover/O,/O his/O attitude/O to/O Kitty/PERSON in/O the/O
past/O--/Othe/O attitude/O of/O a/O grown-up/O person/O to/O a/O child/O,/O arising/O from/O his/O
friendship/O with/O her/O brother/O--/Oseemed/O to/O him/O yet/O another/O obstacle/O to/O love/O./O
An/O ugly/O,/O good-natured/O man/O,/O as/O he/O considered/O himself/O,/O might/O,/O he/O supposed/O,/O
be/O liked/O as/O a/O friend/O;/O but/O to/O be/O loved/O with/O such/O a/O love/O as/O that/O with/O
which/O he/O loved/O Kitty/PERSON,/O one/O would/O need/O to/O be/O a/O handsome/O and/O,/O still/O more/O,/O a/O
distinguished/O man/O./O

He/O had/O heard/O that/O women/O often/O did/O care/O for/O ugly/O and/O ordinary/O men/O,/O but/O he/O
did/O not/O believe/O it/O,/O for/O he/O judged/O by/O himself/O,/O and/O he/O could/O not/O himself/O
have/O loved/O any/O but/O beautiful/O,/O mysterious/O,/O and/O exceptional/O women/O./O

But/O after/O spending/O two/O months/O alone/O in/O the/O country/O,/O he/O was/O convinced/O
that/O this/O was/O not/O one/O of/O those/O passions/O of/O which/O he/O had/O had/O experience/O
in/O his/O early/O youth/O;/O that/O this/O feeling/O gave/O him/O not/O an/O instant/O's/O rest/O;/O
that/O he/O could/O not/O live/O without/O deciding/O the/O question/O,/O would/O she/O or/O would/O
she/O not/O be/O his/O wife/O,/O and/O that/O his/O despair/O had/O arisen/O only/O from/O his/O own/O
imaginings/O,/O that/O he/O had/O no/O sort/O of/O proof/O that/O he/O would/O be/O rejected/O./O And/O
he/O had/O now/O come/O to/O Moscow/LOCATION with/O a/O firm/O determination/O to/O make/O an/O offer/O,/O
and/O get/O married/O if/O he/O were/O accepted/O./O Or/O .../O he/O could/O not/O conceive/O what/O
would/O become/O of/O him/O if/O he/O were/O rejected/O./O



Chapter/O 7/O


On/O arriving/O in/O Moscow/LOCATION by/O a/O morning/O train/O,/O Levin/PERSON had/O put/O up/O at/O the/O house/O
of/O his/O elder/O half-brother/O,/O Koznishev/PERSON./O After/O changing/O his/O clothes/O he/O went/O
down/O to/O his/O brother/O's/O study/O,/O intending/O to/O talk/O to/O him/O at/O once/O about/O the/O
object/O of/O his/O visit/O,/O and/O to/O ask/O his/O advice/O;/O but/O his/O brother/O was/O not/O
alone/O./O With/O him/O there/O was/O a/O well-known/O professor/O of/O philosophy/O,/O who/O had/O
come/O from/O Harkov/PERSON expressly/O to/O clear/O up/O a/O difference/O that/O had/O arisen/O
between/O them/O on/O a/O very/O important/O philosophical/O question/O./O The/O professor/O
was/O carrying/O on/O a/O hot/O crusade/O against/O materialists/O./O Sergey/PERSON Koznishev/PERSON had/O
been/O following/O this/O crusade/O with/O interest/O,/O and/O after/O reading/O the/O
professor/O's/O last/O article/O,/O he/O had/O written/O him/O a/O letter/O stating/O his/O
objections/O./O He/O accused/O the/O professor/O of/O making/O too/O great/O concessions/O to/O
the/O materialists/O./O And/O the/O professor/O had/O promptly/O appeared/O to/O argue/O the/O
matter/O out/O./O The/O point/O in/O discussion/O was/O the/O question/O then/O in/O vogue/O:/O Is/O
there/O a/O line/O to/O be/O drawn/O between/O psychological/O and/O physiological/O
phenomena/O in/O man/O?/O and/O if/O so/O,/O where/O?/O

Sergey/PERSON Ivanovitch/PERSON met/O his/O brother/O with/O the/O smile/O of/O chilly/O friendliness/O
he/O always/O had/O for/O everyone/O,/O and/O introducing/O him/O to/O the/O professor/O,/O went/O
on/O with/O the/O conversation/O./O

A/O little/O man/O in/O spectacles/O,/O with/O a/O narrow/O forehead/O,/O tore/O himself/O from/O
the/O discussion/O for/O an/O instant/O to/O greet/O Levin/PERSON,/O and/O then/O went/O on/O talking/O
without/O paying/O any/O further/O attention/O to/O him/O./O Levin/PERSON sat/O down/O to/O wait/O till/O
the/O professor/O should/O go/O,/O but/O he/O soon/O began/O to/O get/O interested/O in/O the/O
subject/O under/O discussion/O./O

Levin/PERSON had/O come/O across/O the/O magazine/O articles/O about/O which/O they/O were/O
disputing/O,/O and/O had/O read/O them/O,/O interested/O in/O them/O as/O a/O development/O of/O the/O
first/O principles/O of/O science/O,/O familiar/O to/O him/O as/O a/O natural/O science/O
student/O at/O the/O university/O./O But/O he/O had/O never/O connected/O these/O scientific/O
deductions/O as/O to/O the/O origin/O of/O man/O as/O an/O animal/O,/O as/O to/O reflex/O action/O,/O
biology/O,/O and/O sociology/O,/O with/O those/O questions/O as/O to/O the/O meaning/O of/O life/O
and/O death/O to/O himself/O,/O which/O had/O of/O late/O been/O more/O and/O more/O often/O in/O his/O
mind/O./O

As/O he/O listened/O to/O his/O brother/O's/O argument/O with/O the/O professor/O,/O he/O noticed/O
that/O they/O connected/O these/O scientific/O questions/O with/O those/O spiritual/O
problems/O,/O that/O at/O times/O they/O almost/O touched/O on/O the/O latter/O;/O but/O every/O
time/O they/O were/O close/O upon/O what/O seemed/O to/O him/O the/O chief/O point/O,/O they/O
promptly/O beat/O a/O hasty/O retreat/O,/O and/O plunged/O again/O into/O a/O sea/O of/O subtle/O
distinctions/O,/O reservations/O,/O quotations/O,/O allusions/O,/O and/O appeals/O to/O
authorities/O,/O and/O it/O was/O with/O difficulty/O that/O he/O understood/O what/O they/O
were/O talking/O about/O./O

``/OI/O can/Onot/O admit/O it/O,/O''/O said/O Sergey/PERSON Ivanovitch/PERSON,/O with/O his/O habitual/O
clearness/O,/O precision/O of/O expression/O,/O and/O elegance/O of/O phrase/O./O ``/OI/O can/Onot/O in/O
any/O case/O agree/O with/O Keiss/PERSON that/O my/O whole/O conception/O of/O the/O external/O world/O
has/O been/O derived/O from/O perceptions/O./O The/O most/O fundamental/O idea/O,/O the/O idea/O
of/O existence/O,/O has/O not/O been/O received/O by/O me/O through/O sensation/O;/O indeed/O,/O
there/O is/O no/O special/O sense-organ/O for/O the/O transmission/O of/O such/O an/O idea/O./O''/O

``/OYes/O,/O but/O they/O--/OWurt/PERSON,/O and/O Knaust/PERSON,/O and/O Pripasov/PERSON--/Owould/O answer/O that/O your/O
consciousness/O of/O existence/O is/O derived/O from/O the/O conjunction/O of/O all/O your/O
sensations/O,/O that/O that/O consciousness/O of/O existence/O is/O the/O result/O of/O your/O
sensations/O./O Wurt/O,/O indeed/O,/O says/O plainly/O that/O,/O assuming/O there/O are/O no/O
sensations/O,/O it/O follows/O that/O there/O is/O no/O idea/O of/O existence/O./O''/O

``/OI/O maintain/O the/O contrary/O,/O''/O began/O Sergey/PERSON Ivanovitch/PERSON./O

But/O here/O it/O seemed/O to/O Levin/PERSON that/O just/O as/O they/O were/O close/O upon/O the/O real/O
point/O of/O the/O matter/O,/O they/O were/O again/O retreating/O,/O and/O he/O made/O up/O his/O mind/O
to/O put/O a/O question/O to/O the/O professor/O./O

``/OAccording/O to/O that/O,/O if/O my/O senses/O are/O annihilated/O,/O if/O my/O body/O is/O dead/O,/O I/O
can/O have/O no/O existence/O of/O any/O sort/O?/O''/O he/O queried/O./O

The/O professor/O,/O in/O annoyance/O,/O and/O,/O as/O it/O were/O,/O mental/O suffering/O at/O the/O
interruption/O,/O looked/O round/O at/O the/O strange/O inquirer/O,/O more/O like/O a/O bargeman/O
than/O a/O philosopher/O,/O and/O turned/O his/O eyes/O upon/O Sergey/PERSON Ivanovitch/PERSON,/O as/O
though/O to/O ask/O:/O What/O's/O one/O to/O say/O to/O him/O?/O But/O Sergey/PERSON Ivanovitch/PERSON,/O who/O had/O
been/O talking/O with/O far/O less/O heat/O and/O one-sidedness/O than/O the/O professor/O,/O
and/O who/O had/O sufficient/O breadth/O of/O mind/O to/O answer/O the/O professor/O,/O and/O at/O
the/O same/O time/O to/O comprehend/O the/O simple/O and/O natural/O point/O of/O view/O from/O
which/O the/O question/O was/O put/O,/O smiled/O and/O said/O:/O

``/OThat/O question/O we/O have/O no/O right/O to/O answer/O as/O yet/O./O''/O

``/OWe/O have/O not/O the/O requisite/O data/O,/O''/O chimed/O in/O the/O professor/O,/O and/O he/O went/O
back/O to/O his/O argument/O./O ``/ONo/O,/O''/O he/O said/O;/O ``/OI/O would/O point/O out/O the/O fact/O that/O
if/O,/O as/O Pripasov/PERSON directly/O asserts/O,/O perception/O is/O based/O on/O sensation/O,/O then/O
we/O are/O bound/O to/O distinguish/O sharply/O between/O these/O two/O conceptions/O./O''/O

Levin/PERSON listened/O no/O more/O,/O and/O simply/O waited/O for/O the/O professor/O to/O go/O./O



Chapter/O 8/O


When/O the/O professor/O had/O gone/O,/O Sergey/PERSON Ivanovitch/PERSON turned/O to/O his/O brother/O./O

``/ODelighted/O that/O you/O've/O come/O./O For/O some/O time/O,/O is/O it/O?/O How/O's/O your/O farming/O
getting/O on/O?/O''/O

Levin/PERSON knew/O that/O his/O elder/O brother/O took/O little/O interest/O in/O farming/O,/O and/O
only/O put/O the/O question/O in/O deference/O to/O him/O,/O and/O so/O he/O only/O told/O him/O about/O
the/O sale/O of/O his/O wheat/O and/O money/O matters/O./O

Levin/PERSON had/O meant/O to/O tell/O his/O brother/O of/O his/O determination/O to/O get/O married/O,/O
and/O to/O ask/O his/O advice/O;/O he/O had/O indeed/O firmly/O resolved/O to/O do/O so/O./O But/O after/O
seeing/O his/O brother/O,/O listening/O to/O his/O conversation/O with/O the/O professor/O,/O
hearing/O afterwards/O the/O unconsciously/O patronizing/O tone/O in/O which/O his/O
brother/O questioned/O him/O about/O agricultural/O matters/O -LRB-/Otheir/O mother/O's/O
property/O had/O not/O been/O divided/O,/O and/O Levin/PERSON took/O charge/O of/O both/O their/O
shares/O-RRB-/O,/O Levin/PERSON felt/O that/O he/O could/O not/O for/O some/O reason/O begin/O to/O talk/O to/O
him/O of/O his/O intention/O of/O marrying/O./O He/O felt/O that/O his/O brother/O would/O not/O
look/O at/O it/O as/O he/O would/O have/O wished/O him/O to/O./O

``/OWell/O,/O how/O is/O your/O district/O council/O doing/O?/O''/O asked/O Sergey/PERSON Ivanovitch/PERSON,/O who/O
was/O greatly/O interested/O in/O these/O local/O boards/O and/O attached/O great/O
importance/O to/O them/O./O

``/OI/O really/O do/On't/O know/O./O''/O

``/OWhat/O!/O Why/O,/O surely/O you/O're/O a/O member/O of/O the/O board/O?/O''/O

``/ONo/O,/O I/O'm/O not/O a/O member/O now/O;/O I/O've/O resigned/O,/O''/O answered/O Levin/PERSON,/O ``/Oand/O I/O no/O
longer/O attend/O the/O meetings/O./O''/O

``/OWhat/O a/O pity/O!/O''/O commented/O Sergey/PERSON Ivanovitch/PERSON,/O frowning/O./O

Levin/PERSON in/O self-defense/O began/O to/O describe/O what/O took/O place/O in/O the/O meetings/O
in/O his/O district/O./O

``/OThat/O's/O how/O it/O always/O is/O!/O''/O Sergey/PERSON Ivanovitch/PERSON interrupted/O him/O./O ``/OWe/O
Russians/O are/O always/O like/O that/O./O Perhaps/O it/O's/O our/O strong/O point/O,/O really/O,/O
the/O faculty/O of/O seeing/O our/O own/O shortcomings/O;/O but/O we/O overdo/O it/O,/O we/O comfort/O
ourselves/O with/O irony/O which/O we/O always/O have/O on/O the/O tip/O of/O our/O tongues/O./O All/O
I/O say/O is/O,/O give/O such/O rights/O as/O our/O local/O self-government/O to/O any/O other/O
European/O people/O--/Owhy/O,/O the/O Germans/O or/O the/O English/O would/O have/O worked/O their/O
way/O to/O freedom/O from/O them/O,/O while/O we/O simply/O turn/O them/O into/O ridicule/O./O''/O

``/OBut/O how/O can/O it/O be/O helped/O?/O''/O said/O Levin/PERSON penitently/O./O ``/OIt/O was/O my/O last/O
effort/O./O And/O I/O did/O try/O with/O all/O my/O soul/O./O I/O ca/On't/O./O I/O'm/O no/O good/O at/O it/O./O''/O

``/OIt/O's/O not/O that/O you/O're/O no/O good/O at/O it/O,/O''/O said/O Sergey/PERSON Ivanovitch/PERSON;/O ``/Oit/O is/O
that/O you/O do/On't/O look/O at/O it/O as/O you/O should/O./O''/O

``/OPerhaps/O not/O,/O''/O Levin/PERSON answered/O dejectedly/O./O

``/OOh/O!/O do/O you/O know/O brother/O Nikolay/PERSON's/O turned/O up/O again/O?/O''/O

This/O brother/O Nikolay/PERSON was/O the/O elder/O brother/O of/O Konstantin/PERSON Levin/PERSON,/O and/O
half-brother/O of/O Sergey/PERSON Ivanovitch/PERSON;/O a/O man/O utterly/O ruined/O,/O who/O had/O
dissipated/O the/O greater/O part/O of/O his/O fortune/O,/O was/O living/O in/O the/O strangest/O
and/O lowest/O company/O,/O and/O had/O quarreled/O with/O his/O brothers/O./O

``/OWhat/O did/O you/O say/O?/O''/O Levin/PERSON cried/O with/O horror/O./O ``/OHow/O do/O you/O know/O?/O''/O

``/OProkofy/PERSON saw/O him/O in/O the/O street/O./O''/O

``/OHere/O in/O Moscow/LOCATION?/O Where/O is/O he/O?/O Do/O you/O know/O?/O''/O Levin/PERSON got/O up/O from/O his/O chair/O,/O
as/O though/O on/O the/O point/O of/O starting/O off/O at/O once/O./O

``/OI/O am/O sorry/O I/O told/O you/O,/O''/O said/O Sergey/PERSON Ivanovitch/PERSON,/O shaking/O his/O head/O at/O his/O
younger/O brother/O's/O excitement/O./O ``/OI/O sent/O to/O find/O out/O where/O he/O is/O living/O,/O
and/O sent/O him/O his/O IOU/O to/O Trubin/PERSON,/O which/O I/O paid/O./O This/O is/O the/O answer/O he/O sent/O
me/O./O''/O

And/O Sergey/PERSON Ivanovitch/PERSON took/O a/O note/O from/O under/O a/O paper-weight/O and/O handed/O
it/O to/O his/O brother/O./O

Levin/PERSON read/O in/O the/O queer/O,/O familiar/O handwriting/O:/O ``/OI/O humbly/O beg/O you/O to/O
leave/O me/O in/O peace/O./O That/O's/O the/O only/O favor/O I/O ask/O of/O my/O gracious/O
brothers/O./O--/ONikolay/PERSON Levin/PERSON./O''/O

Levin/PERSON read/O it/O,/O and/O without/O raising/O his/O head/O stood/O with/O the/O note/O in/O his/O
hands/O opposite/O Sergey/PERSON Ivanovitch/PERSON./O

There/O was/O a/O struggle/O in/O his/O heart/O between/O the/O desire/O to/O forget/O his/O
unhappy/O brother/O for/O the/O time/O,/O and/O the/O consciousness/O that/O it/O would/O be/O
base/O to/O do/O so/O./O

``/OHe/O obviously/O wants/O to/O offend/O me/O,/O''/O pursued/O Sergey/PERSON Ivanovitch/PERSON;/O ``/Obut/O he/O
can/Onot/O offend/O me/O,/O and/O I/O should/O have/O wished/O with/O all/O my/O heart/O to/O assist/O
him/O,/O but/O I/O know/O it/O's/O impossible/O to/O do/O that/O./O''/O

``/OYes/O,/O yes/O,/O''/O repeated/O Levin/PERSON./O ``/OI/O understand/O and/O appreciate/O your/O attitude/O
to/O him/O;/O but/O I/O shall/O go/O and/O see/O him/O./O''/O

``/OIf/O you/O want/O to/O,/O do/O;/O but/O I/O should/On't/O advise/O it/O,/O''/O said/O Sergey/PERSON Ivanovitch/PERSON./O
``/OAs/O regards/O myself/O,/O I/O have/O no/O fear/O of/O your/O doing/O so/O;/O he/O will/O not/O make/O
you/O quarrel/O with/O me/O;/O but/O for/O your/O own/O sake/O,/O I/O should/O say/O you/O would/O do/O
better/O not/O to/O go/O./O You/O ca/On't/O do/O him/O any/O good/O;/O still/O,/O do/O as/O you/O please/O./O''/O

``/OVery/O likely/O I/O ca/On't/O do/O any/O good/O,/O but/O I/O feel/O--/Oespecially/O at/O such/O a/O
moment/O--/Obut/O that/O's/O another/O thing/O--/OI/O feel/O I/O could/O not/O be/O at/O peace/O./O''/O

``/OWell/O,/O that/O I/O do/On't/O understand/O,/O''/O said/O Sergey/PERSON Ivanovitch/PERSON./O ``/OOne/O thing/O I/O do/O
understand/O,/O''/O he/O added/O;/O ``/Oit/O's/O a/O lesson/O in/O humility/O./O I/O have/O come/O to/O look/O
very/O differently/O and/O more/O charitably/O on/O what/O is/O called/O infamous/O since/O
brother/O Nikolay/PERSON has/O become/O what/O he/O is/O .../O you/O know/O what/O he/O did/O.../O''/O

``/OOh/O,/O it/O's/O awful/O,/O awful/O!/O''/O repeated/O Levin/PERSON./O