We	O
had	O
the	O
chance	O
to	O
speak	O
to	O
Eduardo	PERSON
Hochschild	PERSON
Chairman	POSITION
and	O
controller	O
of	O
Pacasmayo	ORGANIZATION
over	O
the	O
phone.	O
He	O
did	O
not	O
give	O
much	O
away	O
and	O
was	O
very	O
brief	O
so	O
we	O
had	O
to	O
read	O
in	O
between	O
the	O
lines	O
on	O
some	O
comments	O
but	O
think	O
he	O
addressed	O
most	O
topics	O
we	O
wanted	O
to	O
cover.	O
We	O
also	O
squeezed	O
in	O
some	O
questions	O
on	O
Gra&ntilde;a	ORGANIZATION
y	ORGANIZATION
Montero	ORGANIZATION
and	O
the	O
Inmaculada	ORGANIZATION
project	ORGANIZATION
so	O
this	O
is	O
also	O
a	O
read-across	O
Gra&ntilde;a.	ORGANIZATION
GovernanceWhen	ORGANIZATION
we	O
asked	O
about	O
the	O
family	ORGANIZATION
businesses	ORGANIZATION
Eduardo	PERSON
clarified	O
that	O
he	O
is	O
the	O
family.	O
When	O
his	O
father	O
passed	O
away	O
Eduardo	PERSON
took	O
control	O
of	O
the	O
business	O
and	O
if	O
I	O
understood	O
correctly	O
bought	O
his	O
siblings	O
out.	O
Eduardo	PERSON
is	O
the	O
only	O
family	O
member	O
involved	O
in	O
the	O
business	O
and	O
his	O
involvement	O
nowadays	O
is	O
only	O
at	O
the	O
nonexecutive	O
level.	O
Besides	O
Hochschild	ORGANIZATION
Mining	ORGANIZATION
and	O
Pacasmayo	ORGANIZATION
the	O
group	O
also	O
runs	O
an	O
engineering	ORGANIZATION
university	ORGANIZATION
in	O
Peru	LOCATION
and	O
education	O
seems	O
to	O
be	O
one	O
of	O
his	O
areas	O
of	O
interest.	O
However	O
I	O
get	O
the	O
impression	O
his	O
interests	O
here	O
are	O
philanthropic	O
rather	O
than	O
economic.	O
The	ORGANIZATION
miming	ORGANIZATION
company	ORGANIZATION
is	O
not	O
involved	O
in	O
any	O
of	O
Pacasmayo	ORGANIZATION
business	O
so	O
there	O
are	O
no	O
intragroup	O
RPTs.	O
Eduardo	PERSON
made	O
the	O
point	O
that	O
the	O
Hoschild	ORGANIZATION
group	ORGANIZATION
has	O
always	O
had	O
strong	O
governance	O
within	O
the	O
group	O
and	O
having	O
both	O
companies	O
listed	O
in	O
LSE	ORGANIZATION
(Mining)	ORGANIZATION
and	O
NYSE	ORGANIZATION
(Pacasmayo)	ORGANIZATION
are	O
an	O
indication	O
of	O
their	O
high	O
attention	O
to	O
the	O
matter.	O
He	O
counts	O
on	O
strong	O
mgmt.	O
teams	O
for	O
both	O
companies	O
so	O
he	O
does	O
not	O
have	O
to	O
be	O
too	O
involved	O
and	O
he	O
tries	O
to	O
split	O
his	O
time	O
evenly	O
when	O
managing	O
his	O
businesses.	O
There	O
is	O
no	O
succession	O
plan	O
in	O
place	O
at	O
Pacasmayo	ORGANIZATION
but	O
Eduardo	PERSON
is	O
still	O
very	O
young	O
-51	O
and	O
does	O
not	O
seem	O
to	O
be	O
much	O
involved	O
in	O
day-to-day	O
decision	O
making.	O
His	O
sons	O
are	O
also	O
very	O
young	O
(20s)	O
and	O
he	O
does	O
not	O
want	O
them	O
to	O
get	O
involved	O
in	O
the	O
business	O
anytime	O
soon.	O
LT	O
and	O
ST	O
view	O
on	O
PacasmayoOn	ORGANIZATION
Pacasmayo	ORGANIZATION
and	O
the	O
cement	O
industry	O
in	O
Peru	COUNTRY
Eduardo	PERSON
sees	O
some	O
macro	O
ST	O
issues	O
impacting	O
the	O
economy	O
and	O
consequently	O
demand	O
but	O
longer	O
term	O
fundamentals	O
remain	O
intact	O
given	O
Peru's	O
lack	O
of	O
infrastructure	O
and	O
housing	O
deficit	O
which	O
make	O
the	O
industry	O
very	O
promising.	O
In	O
the	O
short	O
term	O
the	O
upcoming	O
elections	O
scheduled	O
for	O
2016	O
bring	O
some	O
uncertainty	O
on	O
the	O
political	O
front	O
and	O
as	O
the	O
CEO	POSITION
pointed	O
out	O
in	O
our	O
previous	O
meeting	O
has	O
been	O
the	O
main	O
reason	O
for	O
delays	O
in	O
infrastructure	O
projects.	O
He	O
also	O
mentioned	O
the	O
effects	O
of	O
El  O
Ni&ntilde;o"	O
on	O
the	O
economy.	O
Depending	O
on	O
the	O
severity	O
of	O
the	O
natural	O
phenomenon	O
it	O
can	O
hinder	O
economic	O
growth	O
especially	O
in	O
the	O
North	LOCATION
region	LOCATION
of	O
Peru	COUNTRY
where	O
the	O
main	O
economic	O
activities	O
besides	O
mining	O
are	O
agriculture	INDUSTRY
and	O
fishing	INDUSTRY
both	O
impacted	O
by	O
the	O
event.	O
M&APacasmayo	ORGANIZATION
wants	O
has	O
ambitions	O
to	O
expand	O
internationally.	O
After	O
Piura	O
is	O
concluded	O
there	O
will	O
not	O
be	O
much	O
room	O
to	O
expand	O
domestically	O
and	O
they	O
are	O
happy	O
with	O
their	O
North	LOCATION
region	LOCATION
monopoly.	O
M&A	ORGANIZATION
seems	O
to	O
be	O
the	O
easiest	O
way	O
to	O
access	O
new	O
markets	O
but	O
so	O
far	O
they	O
have	O
not	O
found	O
anything	O
for	O
the	O
right	O
price	O
and	O
would	O
only	O
make	O
a	O
deal	O
if	O
it	O
makes	O
sense	O
from	O
a	O
valuation	O
point	O
of	O
view.	O
In	O
terms	O
of	O
geographies	O
he	O
mentioned	O
Ecuador	COUNTRY
as	O
an	O
option.	O
They	O
seem	O
to	O
be	O
analyzing	O
opportunities	O
there	O
but	O
are	O
requiring	O
a	O
higher	O
discount	O
to	O
valuation	O
given	O
the	O
current	O
economic	O
environment	O
in	O
the	O
region.	O
He	O
also	O
said	O
that	O
the	O
focus	O
of	O
M&A	ORGANIZATION
will	O
be	O
cement	O
assets.	O
Noncore	O
assetsHe	O
believes	O
Pacasmayo	ORGANIZATION
was	O
fortuned	O
to	O
find	O
a	O
large	O
phosphate	O
reserve	O
close	O
to	O
one	O
of	O
their	O
plants	O
so	O
they	O
decided	O
it	O
would	O
be	O
in	O
the	O
best	O
interest	O
of	O
all	O
shareholders	O
to	O
develop	O
the	O
asset.	O
They	O
will	O
try	O
to	O
bring	O
a	O
new	O
investor	O
to	O
share	O
the	O
capex	O
investments	O
with	O
Mitsubishi	ORGANIZATION
and	O
themselves	O
so	O
capex	O
invested	O
should	O
not	O
be	O
significant.	O
The	O
final	O
study	O
on	O
the	O
project	O
feasibility	O
is	O
still	O
underway.	O
In	O
our	O
previous	O
call	O
the	O
CEO	POSITION
mentioned	O
if	O
they	O
go	O
ahead	O
with	O
the	O
project	O
it	O
will	O
make	O
most	O
sense	O
to	O
spin	O
it	O
off.	O
So	O
the	O
takeaway	O
here	O
is	O
that	O
Pacasmayo	ORGANIZATION
will	O
also	O
have	O
cement	O
as	O
the	O
only	O
core	O
activity	O
but	O
they	O
will	O
take	O
on	O
opportunities	O
that	O
they	O
believe	O
can	O
add	O
value	O
to	O
shareholders.	O
View	O
on	O
GyMWe	O
asked	O
Eduardo's	PERSON
view	O
on	O
Gra&ntilde;a's	ORGANIZATION
execution	O
capabilities	O
given	O
the	O
issues	O
Hochschild	ORGANIZATION
Mining	ORGANIZATION
had	O
with	O
the	O
construction	O
works	O
performed	O
by	O
GyM	ORGANIZATION
at	O
its	O
new	O
mine	O
Inmaculada.	ASSET
Eduardo	PERSON
said	O
that	O
construction	O
works	O
often	O
result	O
in	O
issues	O
that	O
must	O
be	O
dealt	O
with.	O
There	O
were	O
operational	O
hiccups	O
and	O
the	O
development	O
of	O
the	O
mine	O
proved	O
to	O
be	O
more	O
complex	O
than	O
Gra&ntilde;a	ORGANIZATION
and	O
Hochschild	ORGANIZATION
had	O
expected.	O
He	O
avoided	O
making	O
further	O
comments	O
on	O
Gra&ntilde;a	ORGANIZATION
but	O
said	O
he	O
would	O
probably	O
considering	O
Gra&ntilde;a	ORGANIZATION
for	O
future	O
projects.Banorte's	O
AGM	EVENT
was	O
held	O
at	O
their	O
offices	O
in	O
Monterrey	LOCATION
but	O
looks	O
like	O
they	O
rotate	O
every	O
year	O
between	O
Monterrey	LOCATION
and	O
DF.	LOCATION
The	O
meeting	O
is	O
run	O
in	O
a	O
unusual	O
format	O
with	O
board	O
members	O
sitting	O
in	O
a	O
round	O
table	O
facing	O
the	O
projection	O
of	O
a	O
presentation	O
slide	O
and	O
a	O
few	O
other	O
investors	O
sitting	O
in	O
the	O
back.	O
Looking	O
around	O
other	O
than	O
the	O
board	O
members	O
and	O
family	O
reps	O
sitting	O
at	O
the	O
main	O
table	O
I	O
didn't	O
find	O
many	O
institutional	O
investors	O
at	O
the	O
meeting	O
other	O
than	O
ourselves	O
and	O
a	O
couple	O
of	O
lawyers.	O
So	O
although	O
being	O
open	O
to	O
receive	O
investors	O
the	O
meeting	O
was	O
very	O
pro-forma	O
and	O
not	O
much	O
room	O
for	O
questions	O
from	O
the	O
investors	O
present.	O
Worth	O
noting	O
that	O
Banorte's	ORGANIZATION
lawyers	O
doesn't	O
seem	O
to	O
be	O
much	O
flexible	O
to	O
allow	O
investors	O
joining	O
as	O
'observers'	O
only	O
so	O
worth	O
requesting	O
in	O
advance	O
the	O
attend	O
and	O
speak	O
only	O
request	O
to	O
the	O
Proxy	O
team	O
-	O
our	O
request	O
was	O
successfully	O
submitted	O
to	O
the	O
company	O
so	O
our	O
entrance	O
was	O
smooth.With	O
a	O
64%	RATIO
quorum	O
the	O
AGM	EVENT
was	O
installed	O
and	O
all	O
items	O
were	O
approved	O
with	O
no	O
comments.	O
Unlike	O
OMA's	ORGANIZATION
AGM	EVENT
where	O
all	O
documents	O
were	O
read	O
at	O
the	O
meeting	O
at	O
Banorte's	ORGANIZATION
they	O
only	O
read	O
the	O
key	O
points	O
so	O
a	O
much	O
quicker	O
meeting	O
-	O
similar	O
to	O
the	O
procedure	O
in	O
Brazil	COUNTRY
and	O
Chile.	COUNTRY
Carlos	PERSON
Hank	PERSON
chairmanship	POSITION
was	O
approved	O
by	O
shareholders	O
and	O
all	O
members	O
sitting	O
at	O
the	O
desk	O
went	O
to	O
congratulate	O
him	O
after	O
the	O
meeting.	O
At	O
least	O
the	O
appearance	O
was	O
of	O
a	O
friendly	O
environment.	O
By	O
the	O
end	O
of	O
the	O
meeting	O
I	O
introduced	O
myself	O
to	O
Carlos	PERSON
Hank	PERSON
who	O
thanked	O
our	O
presence	O
at	O
the	O
AGM	EVENT
and	O
support.	O
He	O
had	O
to	O
rush-off	O
so	O
not	O
much	O
time	O
for	O
a	O
proper	O
chat.	O
